In June 2025, Britain and Spain signed a
treaty that seemed
politically impossible.
To tear down the border fence, the UK had
to agree to a massive red line,
allowing EU border guards
to stand on British soil.
Every day about 15,000 people cross the
border between Spain and Gibraltar.
Most of them are Spanish workers heading
to jobs on the rock.
The town on the Spanish side, La Linea de
la Concepcion, has 35% unemployment.
Gibraltar has about
2.5%. They need each other.
On paper, the physical border is gone.
But in the fine print of that 2025 deal,
is a phrase that ruins the mood. Without
prejudice to sovereignty,
it means that after the three centuries,
we still haven't
solved the actual problem.
That argument goes back to
a single document from 1713.
And in that document is a clause that has
effectively blocked 34,000 people
from deciding their own
future for over three centuries.
One side says Gibraltar is British. They
voted 99% to stay in the British Empire.
The other side says it's
stolen land that belongs to Spain.
They're both making real legal arguments.
And that's exactly the problem.
So how did Britain end up with a 6.8
square kilometer rock
at the bottom of Spain?
In 1704, Britain was fighting
the War of Spanish Succession.
A massive European conflict over who
would sit on the Spanish throne.
An Anglo-Dutch fleet of
about 62 warships was failing.
Their attack on the city of Cadiz had
fallen apart because the British troops,
and this is from the reports,
disintegrated in an orgy of drunkenness.
An attempted uprising in
Barcelona produced nothing.
The commanders needed
a win. A council of war
chose Gibraltar because it was, in their
words, "indifferently garrisoned".
That's 18th century
language for "barely defended".
Somewhere between 80 and 150 regular
soldiers, depending on the source,
plus a few hundred militia.
On August 1, 1704, about 2,000 marines
landed on the Isthmus.
Three days of bombardment,
roughly 15,000 rounds fired.
On August 4, the
Spanish governor surrendered.
Britain didn't plan to keep it.
Peter Gold, one of the leading scholars
on Gibraltar, writes that initially no
interest was shown from London in
accepting responsibility
for the administration of
Gibraltar. British ministers considered
giving it back at least seven times in
the following 15 years.
On July 13, 1713, Spain and Britain
signed the Treaty of
Utrecht, ending the war.
The British negotiators had realized that
controlling the
entrance to the Mediterranean
was too valuable to hand
back. So they wrote Article X.
Here's what it actually says. It's
written in what
scholars call "dog Latin",
a clunky, simplified version of Latin
that 18th century
diplomats used for contracts.
It sounds authoritative,
but it's full of ambiguity.
The Catholic king does hereby, for
himself, his heirs and successors, yield
to the crown of Great
Britain the full and entire property of
the town and castle of Gibraltar,
together with the port,
fortifications, and
forts thereunto belonging.
That's the cession.
Spain gave Britain the rock.
But notice this specific phrase. "The
above named property be
yielded to Great Britain
without any territorial jurisdiction and
without any open communication by land
with the country roundabout." Britain got
a rock and the walls
around it, not one meter beyond.
And this is where the border dispute
actually starts. That flat
strip of land connecting the
rock to Spain, the Isthmus, wasn't part
of the deal. In 1713 it was
neutral ground. Nobody was
supposed to build on it. But in 1814 a
wave of yellow fever hit Gibraltar.
People were dying in
the cramped city, so Britain asked Spain
for permission to move
civilians onto that empty
flat land to build temporary hospital
huts. Spain agreed. It
was a health emergency.
Britain never left. They replaced the
huts with permanent
buildings. Eventually they built the
airport runway right across it. To Spain
that's not just a border
dispute. That's 200 years of
squatting on land that was never part of
the original treaty. But
the Isthmus isn't the real
problem. The real problem is what comes
next in Article 10. And in
case it shall hereafter seem
to meet to the crown of Great Britain, to
grant, sell, or by any means to alienate,
the preference of having the same shall
always be given to the crown
of Spain before any others.
In plain English, if Britain ever gives
up Gibraltar or changes
its status, they have to
offer it to Spain first. Think about what
that means for the people
living there. In most places
the population can eventually push for
their right to govern
themselves. But for Gibraltar,
any move towards self-governance risks
being interpreted as
Britain alienating the territory.
And the moment that happens, the clause
says "the rock goes to
Spain". The UK government has
confirmed this in writing. Under the
Treaty of Utrecht,
independence is not an option,
unless Spain is prepared to agree. 34,000
people locked into a choice
between British and Spanish
by a sentence written in dog Latin over
300 years ago. Spain didn't
just sign the treaty and move on.
They tried to take Gibraltar back. The
biggest attempt was the
Great Siege, 1779-1783.
Three years, seven months, twelve days.
It's the longest siege in
British military history.
Spain and France threw 40,000 troops, 246
guns, and ten specially
designed floating batteries at
about 7,000 British defenders under
General Eliott. In a letter from 1782,
King George III admits that
he would rather get rid of Gibraltar if
possible. But the garrison's
success made that politically
impossible. Strong as the rock of
Gibraltar entered the
English language, Mozart wrote
a commemorative piece. After 1783, giving
back the rock wasn't just a
bad idea, it was unthinkable.
The Great Siege turned Gibraltar into a
British symbol. But it was
a 20th century dictator who
turned the people living on it into a
nation. Because the people
living on that rock weren't
originally British. They were Genoese,
Maltese, Sephardic Jewish, Moroccan,
Portuguese, and Spanish.
They spoke a language called "Llanito", a
mix of old and
Andalusian Spanish and English.
Until the late 1950s, 85% of children
started school speaking
only Spanish. So what changed?
In the 1960s, the United Nations was
pushing for decolonization, pressuring
European empires to give
up their overseas territories. The
Spanish dictator Francisco Franco
expected the UN to force
Britain's hand and deliver Gibraltar back
to Spain. But in 1967,
Gibraltar held a referendum.
The question was clear. Pass under
Spanish sovereignty or
retain the link with Britain.
12,138 voted to stay British. 44 voted
for Spain. That's 99.64%.
Franco was furious. On June 8, 1969, he
shut the border completely.
Land, sea, telephone lines,
all cut. 16 years of total isolation.
Overnight, Gibraltar lost
a third of its workforce.
About 13,500 Spanish workers who
crossed daily. Britain flew in Moroccan
replacements within two weeks.
Gibraltarian women entered the
workforce. The military baked the bread
and collected the rubbish.
And on Sundays, families would stand at
the closed border and scream
news across the neutral ground.
Parents held up newborn babies for
grandparents in Spain to
see through binoculars.
One woman stood at the fence in her
wedding dress so her grandmother on the Spanish side could watch
from across the border. Franco thought
he'd starve them into
surrendering. Instead,
he did the opposite. English became a
marker of loyalty. Being not Spanish
became the core of a
new identity. By the time the border
reopened in 1985, the people behind it
weren't just occupants
of a British rock. They were
Gibraltarians. Since then, the people of
Gibraltar have voted three
times in their future. And every time it
didn't matter. 1967,
99.64% voted to stay British.
Three months later, the UN General
Assembly passed Resolution
2353, calling the referendum
a contravention of decolonization
principles. The reasoning was that
Gibraltar's colonial
status destroys the national unity and
territorial integrity of
Spain. The vote didn't count.
2002, Britain and Spain proposed shared
sovereignty. 98.97% voted against. The UK
Foreign Secretary called the referendum
eccentric and said the
results wouldn't be recognized.
2016, Brexit. Gibraltar voted 95.91% to
remain in the EU. The strongest
remain vote anywhere in Britain. They
were pulled out anyway. Three votes, near
unanimous each time,
overruled, dismissed and ignored. Now, if
we are being fair to
Spain, their argument isn't just
their leftover from Franco. This is a
position held by every Spanish
government, left and right,
going all the way back to Queen
Isabella's will in 1504, where she wrote,
"I ask and require of
the kings, my successors, that they may
hold and retain the said city for
themselves and in their
own possession." Spain's legal case rests
on territorial integrity.
The idea that the colonial
power shouldn't be allowed to carve out a
permanent chunk of
another country's land.
Legal scholars like Jamie Trinidad at
Cambridge point out that the UN
distinguishes between
self-determination and territorial
integrity. In Gibraltar's
case, those two principles
directly conflict. Spain argues the
current population was
brought in by Britain after the
original Spanish residents were expelled.
So, in their view, the
votes of 34,000 people
shouldn't override the integrity of the
Spanish map. It's a serious legal
argument, but Spain has
a contradiction to deal with. Spain holds
two cities on the coast of
Africa, Ceuta and Melilla.
Ceuta has been under Spanish or
Portuguese control since
1415, Melilla since 1497.
Morocco claims them both, using the exact
same arguments Spain uses for Gibraltar.
Geographic proximity, territorial
integrity, colonial legacy.
There are real differences.
Ceuta and Melilla aren't on the UN's list
of non-self-governing
territories. Their residents
have full Spanish citizenship and
representation in Spanish Parliament,
which Gibraltarians don't
have. Spain argues their integral parts
of the Spanish state, not
colonies. But the parallel is
hard to ignore. King Hassan II of Morocco
once predicted that the
day Britain leaves Gibraltar,
international pressure will force Spain
out of its African
cities. Spain knows this and it
constrains everything they do. Which
brings us back to the 2025 treaty.
The fence is coming down. Defense is expected to
come down once the agreement is
provisionally applied.
Spanish workers won't have to queue
for hours anymore. For the 15,000 people
who crossed the border
daily, life is said to get
easier. But the 2025 agreement includes
its own version of the same old phrase,
"without prejudice to sovereignty".
Defense is said to ease. The
question of who owns the
rock does not get answered. And article
10 is still there. The
preference of having the same
shall always be given to the crown of
Spain before any others. The people of
Gibraltar are a modern,
democratic society that still can't fully
govern themselves because
of a sentence written in
dog Latin over 300 years ago. They can't
be Spanish, 99% of them have said so
repeatedly. They can't
be fully self-governing. The reversionary
clause blocks that path.
And they're increasingly
frustrated with being governed from
London by a country that just pulled them
out of the EU against
their will. The 2025 treaty is said to
make the border easier to
cross. It doesn't change the
contract that built it. If you want more
primary sources
analyzed, please subscribe.