This document created one of the first
constitutional democracies in Asia.
December 30th 1906.
The Shah signed it and
then died five days later.
But the Constitution survived.
Iran had an elected parliament before
most of the Middle East,
before the Russian Revolution,
before the Ottoman
Constitution was restored.
And then foreign powers destroyed it.
Twice.
Right now Iranians are
in the streets again.
Same demands. Same pattern.
And most people have no idea this fight
started 120 years ago.
If you ask online about the situation in
Iran, you'll get two answers.
One side says it's America's fault.
The 1953 coup
destroyed Iranian democracy.
Everything since then is blowback.
The other side says Iran is just
culturally authoritarian.
Nothing will change until they
have their own enlightenment.
So I did some digging, read some books
about the topic and then
went to the primary sources.
The truth is both narratives are wrong.
And they're wrong because
they start in the wrong place.
Everyone talks about 1953.
The CIA coup, that's the story.
But 1953 wasn't the beginning.
It was a repetition.
Let's start with 1906.
The pattern starts there.
Iranians build a
constitutional democracy.
Foreign powers found it inconvenient.
These foreign powers allied
with domestic authoritarians.
And this led to the destruction of the
constitutional government.
1953 was the second time that happened.
Not the first.
And understanding the first time explains
why the second time worked.
And why the trauma runs so deep.
December 1905.
Tehran.
The governor ordered several sugar
merchants beaten with the bastinado.
That's a punishment where they whipped
the soles of your feet.
Because they refused to lower prices
during an economic crisis.
This seems like a small thing.
A local dispute.
But the sources reveal why it exploded.
At this time Iran was
ruled by the Qajar dynasty.
A royal family that had
been in power since 1789.
And the Qajars had a problem.
They were broke.
The revolution's long-term causes were
rooted in the 19th century.
Its short-term ones were
triggered in 1904 and 1905.
By an economic crisis brought about by
government bankruptcy
and spiraling inflation.
For decades the Qajars had been selling
off pieces of Iran to foreign powers.
Telegraph rights, banking
rights, tobacco rights, oil rights.
Each sale made the Shah more dependent on
foreigners and less
responsive to Iranians.
So when the governor beat those
merchants, he wasn't just
enforcing price controls.
He was defending a system that had sold
the country piece by piece.
While ordinary people starved.
And that's when
something unprecedented happened.
The merchants took bast—sanctuary.
First in mosques.
Then in the garden of
the British embassy.
What makes this different from other
Middle Eastern protests of that era is
the direction it went.
While in Egypt the British were
dissolving parliaments.
In Iran protesters were demanding one.
And using British territory to do it.
While in the Ottoman Empire the 1876
constitution had been
granted from above by the Sultan.
In Iran the constitution was being
demanded from below.
By merchants, intellectuals and dissident
clerics working together.
By August 1906 there were 14,000 people
camped in the British Legation Garden.
And what they demanded was a majlis, a
parliament and
constitutional limits on the Shah's power.
They won.
On October 7th 1906
the first majlis opened.
On December 30th the Shah
signed the constitution.
But this wasn't just a symbolic document.
It was an operational
manual for limiting royal power.
The majlis elected representatives from
across Iran had to approve all budgets,
treaties, loans and concessions.
They could question
ministers and force them to resign.
They even controlled the court budget.
Every mechanism the Qajars had used to
sell off Iran was now
under parliamentary control.
The constitution was
modeled on Belgium's.
Itself derived from British
constitutional principles.
Iran had created on paper a genuine
constitutional monarchy.
And the part that matters is this.
It wasn't imposed by foreigners.
It grew from internal pressure.
Iranians themselves built this.
Which is exactly why foreign powers
decided to destroy it.
One year later in 1907 Britain faced a
problem that had nothing to do with Iran.
Germany was rising.
The Royal Navy needed allies.
And the only power that could
counterbalance
Germany on land was Russia.
But Britain and Russia had been rivals in
Central Asia for decades.
They had been competing for influence in
Persia, Afghanistan and Tibet.
A rivalry the British
called the Great Game.
To get Russia as an ally against Germany,
Britain needed to
settle these Asian disputes.
So they signed the
Anglo-Russian Convention.
Britain got southern Iran
as its sphere of influence.
Russia got northern Iran.
A neutral zone set between them.
The critical detail is this.
Iran was not consulted but was simply
informed of this arrangement after the
treaty was signed in St Petersburg.
Iran wasn't at the table.
They were on the menu.
And this created a fundamental problem.
The constitutional government that the
Iranians had just built depended on
controlling concessions.
But Britain and Russia had just divided
up their right to grant
concessions between themselves.
The constitution was
designed to limit foreign influence.
The Anglo-Russian Convention
was designed to guarantee it.
Something had to give.
The new Shah, Mohammed Ali
Shah, saw his opportunity.
The constitution limited his power.
Russia and Britain had just shown it
didn't care about the constitution.
So in 1908 he moved to destroy it.
At this time the Shah's most reliable
military force was the Cossack Brigade.
An Iranian unit trained and
commanded by Russian officers.
Declaring martial law, the Shah appointed
Colonel Lyakhov, the Russian Cossack
commander, to be
military governor of Tehran.
Lyakhov sent his Cossacks to occupy the
telegraph office and to
bombard the Majlis building.
Do you see what happened here?
The Iranian parliament was
bombarded by Iranian troops.
Commanded by a Russian officer appointed
by an Iranian Shah with the tacit approval
of Britain and Russia.
Who had just divided
Iran between themselves.
Foreign intervention and domestic
authoritarianism working together.
About 250 people died.
The Majlis building was destroyed.
The constitutional forces fought back.
They retook Tehran.
They restored the Majlis.
But in 1911, Russia
delivered an ultimatum.
The Majlis had hired an American
financial advisor named Morgan Shuster to
fix Iran's finances and
reduce foreign influence.
Russia demanded his
dismissal or they would occupy.
The Majlis refused.
So Russia occupied.
The second Majlis was closed in December
1911 and Shuster's contract was abruptly
terminated a few weeks later.
With the closure of the Majlis, the first
phase of the revolution effectively came
to a stuttering halt.
Iran's first democracy crushed and this
is what it established.
Iranians built
constitutional institutions.
Foreign powers find those
institutions inconvenient.
Foreign powers ally with
domestic authoritarians.
Constitutional government is destroyed
and that trauma creates demand for the
next constitutional movement.
1906 to 1911, that's the
first turn of the cycle.
For the next decades,
Iran descended into chaos.
World War I, foreign occupation, famine,
a new dynasty, Reza Shah, who kept the
constitutional form
but gutted its substance.
Then World War II.
Britain and the Soviets occupied Iran
again, forcing Reza Shah to abdicate.
His son, Mohammad Reza,
took the throne at 21.
He was weak.
The Majlis had space to act again and the
men who would lead the
revival had been waiting.
A 69-year-old aristocrat who had spent
his entire political career fighting for
constitutional government.
Back in 1919, when Britain tried to make
Iran a protectorate through the
Anglo-Persian agreement,
this man stood up in the Majlis and
called the negotiators
traitors to their faces.
His name was Mohammad Mosadegh.
I'll be honest, before I did research I
had a simple picture of Mosadegh.
National hero,
overturned by the CIA, a victim.
The sources complicate that picture.
Not in the way that you might think, the
CIA still overthrew him.
But understanding who he was explains
both why he succeeded and why he failed.
Mosadegh wasn't a young revolutionary.
He'd been fighting for constitutional
government since 1906.
He was an aristocrat, educated
in Europe, wealthy, connected.
And he had one absolute conviction.
Iran must control its own resources.
This wasn't a man who
compromised with foreign powers.
Mosadegh's conviction would be tested on
one issue above all others.
Oil.
Since 1901, British interests had
controlled Iranian oil through something
called the D'Arcy Concession.
The deal worked like this.
The concession gave British investors 60
years of exclusive rights to Iranian oil.
Iran got 16% of net profits.
And the British controlled how net
profits were calculated.
The British controlled oil drilling,
refining and export operations.
And by 1914, the British government owned
51% of the Anglo-Iranian oil company,
which would later become BP.
But what I found interesting is that
Iran's profit share
wasn't even the core issue.
British Petroleum Archives and Foreign
Office records show that the core of the
dispute was not profit
sharing, but control.
A March 1951 memo stated, "We can be
flexible in profits, administration or
partnership, but not in
the issue of control."
The British would share money, they
wouldn't share power.
So when Mosadegh proposed
nationalization, not confiscation,
nationalization with compensation, it
wasn't radical by global standards.
Saudi Arabia had just negotiated a 50-50
profit split with Aramco.
Venezuela had done the same.
Iran was asking for what
others had already achieved.
But there was a difference.
Saudi Arabia and Venezuela negotiated
from within the system.
Mosadegh wanted to
change the system itself.
On March 15, 1951, the
Majlis voted to nationalize oil.
96 deputies showed up, including several
who had promised the
Shah they would stay away.
Everyone voted in
favor of nationalization.
Even deputies who had promised the Shah
they would boycott
showed up and voted yes.
That's how popular nationalization was.
This wasn't Mosadegh imposing his will.
This was the Majlis, the
constitutional institution Iranians had
been fighting for since
1906, exercising its authority.
And that's precisely when
Britain couldn't accept it.
Britain refused to negotiate.
Sir William Fraser, the chairman of the
Anglo-Iranian oil company, put it simply,
"There will be no further concessions."
When negotiation failed,
Britain turned to covert action.
But they had a problem.
Britain couldn't
overthrow Mossadegh alone.
They needed American help.
And in 1952, President Truman wasn't
interested in coups.
Then Eisenhower won the 1952 election.
And the British found a
way to get American support.
Christopher Woodhouse was the MI6 officer
who helped plan the operation.
This is how he described their strategy.
I decided to emphasize the communist
threat to Iran rather than the need to
recover control of the oil industry.
The British reframed the issue.
This wasn't about oil anymore.
This was about communism.
And the causal chain matters.
Britain couldn't
overthrow Mosadegh alone.
They needed American power.
And the only way to get American power
was to make Iran about
the Cold War, not about oil.
Consequently, a 69-year-old
constitutional nationalist became, in
American eyes, a communist threat.
This is how the coup actually worked.
Not the narrative, the mechanism.
The operation had two names.
The British called it Operation Boot.
The Americans called it TPAJAX.
The CIA budgeted $150,000 for propaganda
alone, plus additional funds for bribing
members of the Majlis.
They bribed newspapers to print
anti-Mosadegh stories.
They paid clerics to preach against
communist influence.
They purchased deputies for a
no-confidence vote.
They organized street
mobs with paid demonstrators.
And when the moment was right, military
units would complete the overthrow.
But the part that
most people miss is this.
The CIA didn't just organize a coup.
They manufactured the communist threat
they claimed to be fighting against.
Iran did have a
communist party, the Tudeh.
But the Tudeh wasn't
allied with Mosadegh.
The CIA decided to make
it look like they were.
Black propaganda means fake materials
designed to look like
they came from the enemy.
The CIA printed fake Tudeh leaflets,
threatening religious leaders with savage
punishment if they opposed Mosadegh,
to create the appearance of a communist
threat, to justify removing him.
August 15th, 1953,
the first coup attempt.
The plan was for the Shah to sign a
decree dismissing Mosadegh and appointing
General Fazlollah Zahedi.
A military officer the British and
Americans had chosen as
the new prime minister.
Military units would
then arrest Mosadegh.
But someone in the plot leaked the plan.
Mosadegh found out.
He arrested the officer who
came to deliver the decree.
The coup had failed.
The Shah fled to Rome.
Washington sent a cable ordering the
operation discontinued.
In view forgoing and in absence strong
contrary recommendations from you and
Ambassador Henderson,
operations against
Mosadegh should be discontinued.
Kermit Roosevelt, the CIA officer running
the operation in
Tehran, ignored the order.
August 19th, Roosevelt organized paid
mobs to flood the streets, creating chaos
and the appearance of
popular opposition to Mosadegh.
Military units that had been paid off
moved on Mosadegh's house.
Richard Cottam, who was on CIA staff,
later admitted what
those crowds actually were.
That mob that came into North Tehran and
was decisive in the
overthrow was a mercenary mob.
It had no ideology.
And that mob was paid
with American dollars.
By evening, Mosadegh was under arrest.
Zahedi was prime minister.
And the Shah returned from Rome.
The CIA's own internal history,
declassified in 2013, states it plainly.
The military coup that overthrew Mosadegh
and his National Front Cabinet was
carried out under CIA direction as an act
of US foreign policy, conceived and
approved at the
highest level of government.
At his trial, Mosadegh said, "My only
crime is that I nationalized the Iranian
oil industry and removed from this land
the network of colonialism and the
political and economic influence of the
greatest empire on earth."
He was sentenced to three years in
prison, then house arrest for life.
He died in 1967,
still under house arrest.
The government didn't
permit the public funeral.
Iran's second democracy crushed.
Now, if you've been following the
evidence, you might think the America's
fault narrative sounds pretty accurate.
The CIA did overthrow a
democratic government.
The documents prove it.
And the CIA admitted it.
And the trauma this created is real.
After 1953, Iranian politics became
saturated with conspiracy thinking.
Political polemics in Iran are replete
with such terms as
"tuteah," "jasous," "khianat."
These words—plot, spy, treason—became central to
how Iranians talked about politics.
Every event got
explained as foreign conspiracy.
Every politician got
suspected of being a foreign agent.
This vocabulary treats Iranian politics
as a puppet show, in which the real
players are hidden hands.
The belief that real decisions are made
by foreign powers
operating behind the scenes.
That's the psychological legacy of 1953.
Every regime since then has
used the coup as justification.
Every failure gets blamed
on foreign conspiracies.
So, where does this narrative go wrong?
The coup was foreign planned,
but it was Iranian executed.
The events were steered, executed and
operationalized by Iranians,
who were directly and indirectly carrying
out modified British US plans.
Mosaddegh and his colleagues made a
number of key strategic
and tactical mistakes.
Most importantly, they
failed to create an organization,
capable of mobilizing broad
support for their movement.
Foreign powers provided
the plan and the money.
Iranians provided the execution.
And Mosaddegh made mistakes.
He held referendums with separate ballot
boxes for yes and no.
Anyone could see how you voted.
That's not real democracy.
He took emergency powers
that alienated former allies.
He knew General Zahedi was plotting
against him, but didn't act decisively.
Does this justify the coup?
No.
But it explains why the coup succeeded.
The CIA didn't
overthrow a unified government.
They exploited
divisions that already existed.
And the deeper problem is
treating 1953 as the beginning.
As we've seen, the
pattern started in 1907.
The 1953 coup wasn't a
rupture in Iranian history.
It was a repetition.
The same pattern, different players.
And treating 1953 as the original sin
means waiting for America
to fix what America broke.
That's not a political program.
That's learned helplessness.
So this is what the
evidence actually shows.
The 1953 coup wasn't unique.
It was the second verse
of a song started in 1906.
But what makes this a cycle, not just
repetition, is what happened next.
Each suppression
radicalized the next generation.
The trauma of 1953 shaped
everything that came after.
In 1979, Iranians rose up again.
Millions in the street.
They overthrew the Shah.
They promised democracy.
And then something strange happened.
The revolution had promised freedom,
created a new system of control.
One that would prove even harder to
challenge than the Shahs.
How did that happen?
And what does it mean that Iranians are
still fighting the same
fight 120 years later?
That is part two.