This is Pete Hegseth, current US
Secretary of Defense.
He has a tattoo that says "Deus Vult",
Latin for "God wills it", that was the war
cry of the first crusade.
A viral video with nearly 5 million views
argues the crusades were defensive,
justified and "awesome".
In this video, you'll be finding out why
the crusades were not only morally
justified, but were
actually a historic achievement.
This narrative is being used right now.
Both Christian nationalists and Islamist
extremists use distorted crusades history
to justify modern conflicts.
The video makes 5 major claims. Every one
of them leaves out critical evidence.
I went to the primary sources, what the
crusaders themselves
wrote about what they did.
And it's not what this video tells you.
This is Fulcher of Chartres.
He was a Christian chaplain who
participated in the first crusade.
Here's what he wrote about the
capture of Jerusalem in 1099.
About 10,000 were beheaded, not one of
them was allowed to live. They did not
spare women and children.
That's from a Christian source, not
Muslim propaganda. A
crusader's own account.
Now, before I go further, let me be very
clear. The video I'm fact
checking gets some things right.
The Byzantine and Sassanid empires did
fight a devastating 25 year war that left
them vulnerable to Arab conquest.
The Battle of Manzikert in 1071 was a
major defeat for Byzantium.
Emperor Alexios did appeal
to the Pope for military help.
And yes, Islamic expansion in the 7th and
8th centuries was
conquest. These are facts.
The problem isn't the facts the video
presents. It's the facts it leaves out.
The first crusade could really only be
qualified as a roaring success.
Remember, the video calls the first
crusade a roaring success.
Militarily, sure, the crusaders won their
battles and captured Jerusalem.
But here's what the video
doesn't mention about that success.
On July 15th, 1099, crusader forces
breached the walls of Jerusalem.
What happened next is documented in
multiple Christian sources.
In the temple and porch of Solomon, men
rode in blood up to
their knees and bridal rains.
That's Raymond d'Aguilers, another
eyewitness. He continues.
"Indeed, it was a just and splendid
judgment of God that this place should be
filled with the blood
of the unbelievers."
The anonymous author of the
Gesta Francorum, another crusader
chronicle, wrote that the slaughter was
so great that our men waited
in blood up to their ankles.
Modern historians estimate
around 3,000 people were killed.
Some medieval sources
claimed tens of thousands.
Either way, this was a massacre. And it
wasn't just Muslims.
The Muslim chronicler Ibn al-Qalanisi
recorded that the Jews had gathered in
their synagogue and the
Franks burned it over their heads.
All this isn't in the
"Awesome Crusades" video.
The video calls the Crusades a defensive
war against Muslim expansion.
So let me tell you what the Fourth
Crusade actually did.
Some Crusades were huge successes, like
the Reconquista, while others were dismal
failures, like the Fourth Crusade.
But even the failures are
understandable in context.
The Fourth Crusade was supposed to
liberate Jerusalem by attacking Egypt.
Instead, the Crusaders went massively
into debt to Venice.
34,000 silver marks they couldn't pay.
So in 1204, they attacked Constantinople.
Not a Muslim city, the capital of the
Byzantine Empire, the
greatest Christian power in the East.
They sacked a Christian city.
They looted Christian churches. And they
killed Orthodox Christians.
The Byzantine senator,
Niketas Choniates, was there.
He called the Crusaders, and I quote
again, "four runners of antichrists,
agents of his anticipated ungodly deeds."
They broke into the Hagia Sophia, smashed
the altar, and brought in
mules to haul away gold.
The prostitutes sat in the patriarch's
seat, singing obscene songs.
Even Pope Innocent III condemned them
once he learned what happened.
Here's what he wrote.
"They have spared neither age nor sex.
They have exposed both matrons and
virgins, even those dedicated to God, to
the sordid lusts of boys."
The Fourth Crusade destroyed the
Byzantine Empire. It never recovered.
This made the Ottoman
conquest easier, not harder.
Calling this an understandable failure is
like calling the Titanic a minor setback.
The video frames the Crusades as
Christians defending
themselves against Muslim aggression.
But here's something
the video doesn't mention.
The Crusaders killed thousands of Jews
before they even left Europe.
In 1096, Crusader armies marched through
the Rhineland, modern-day Germany.
They attacked Jewish communities in
Speyer, Worms, Mainz, and Cologne.
Estimates ranged from
3,000 to 5,000 dead.
The Christian chronicler Albert of Aachen
records their justification.
The beginning of their expedition and
their duty against the
enemies of the Christian faith.
Their logic? Why fight enemies of Christ
in Jerusalem when they live amongst us?
That's not defending Christianity. That's
religious violence against
anyone deemed an outsider.
And the atrocities didn't stop there.
At the siege of Mara in
1098, Crusaders were starving.
Here's what Fulcher of Chartres. Again, a
Christian chaplain wrote.
"Many of our people, harassed by
excessive hunger, cut pieces from the
buttocks of the Saracens already dead
there, which they cooked and
devoured with savage mouth."
Another Crusader recorded.
"We greedily ate the already feted bodies
of the Saracens thrown into the swamp two
or more weeks before."
Again, this isn't Muslim propaganda.
These are Christian
Crusaders describing what they did.
"Christian inhabitants had to pay an
enormous tax called the dhimmi tax."
The video claims Christians under Muslim
rule paid an enormous
tax called the jizya.
Let's look at the actual numbers.
Wealthy, four dinners per year, middle
class two dinners per year, and the poor
one dinner per year.
This was paid by adult males only. Not
women, not children. And it exempted them
from military service.
Muslims paid a similar tax called zakat.
Now, let's compare this
to Christian kingdoms.
Jews in medieval Europe faced arbitrary
taxes, forced
conversions and outright expulsion.
England expelled all Jews in 1290, France
in 1306 and Spain in 1492.
The historian Mark R. Cohen notes that
dhimmi status, while second class,
compares favorably with the treatment of
non-Christians in Europe.
Was the jizya a burden? Yes.
Was it enormous compared to Christian
treatment of
minorities? That needs context.
The video blames Islamic piracy for
turning the Mediterranean into an unsafe
hellhole and crashing the European
economy for 400 years.
Let me show you what the video
conveniently ignores.
The Vikings, from the 9th century onward,
Norse raiders devastated European coasts.
They plundered London, Paris, Cologne,
Kiev. They raided as far as Pisa and
Florence. They weren't Muslim.
And economic decline, the
Western Roman Empire collapsed.
The Byzantine-Sassanate
war devastated the East.
Blaming 400 years of problems solely on
Muslim pirates ignores basically
everything else that happened.
Europe was Christian when the Crusades
were launched and it's still majority
Christian today, 1000 years later,
although it is secularizing due to
modernist ideologies.
Ironically, it's only after the Pope lost
his power to call Crusades that
Christianity started
to decline in Europe.
Let's check the timeline.
The Crusades ended around 1300.
European secularization began in the
1700s with the Enlightenment.
Time gap? About 400 years.
In between you had the Protestant
Reformation, Christians splitting into
war infections, the 30 years war,
Christians killing Christians, the
scientific revolution.
By the video's logic I could claim Europe
speaks Indo-European
languages because of the Crusades.
Correlation isn't
causation. And here's the kicker.
Christian territory was lost despite the
Crusades. Anatolia became Turkey. The
Balkans fell to the Ottomans.
The Ford Crusade weakened the Byzantine
Empire, making the
Ottoman conquest easier.
The Crusades didn't
preserve Christianity in Europe.
Geography did. Early Carolingian defense
did. Byzantine resilience did.
Historians across the board rejected the
awesome Crusades narrative.
The medieval reality was messy.
Reciprocal violence, trade, diplomacy,
and yes, atrocities on both sides.
Simplifying 200 years of history into
"good guys vs bad guys"
doesn't honor the past.
It weaponizes it.
Look, I'm not saying the
Crusades were uniquely evil.
Medieval warfare was brutal across the
board. Muslim armies
committed massacres too.
But if you're going to make a video with
5 million views called "Why the Crusades
Were Awesome", you can't just erase the
parts where Crusaders massacred
civilians, sacked Christian
cities, and ate their enemies.
Every source I've cited today
is in the description below.
History isn't simple. The
Crusades weren't either.