In May 2025, Britain signed
away its last African colony.
Headlines called it historic.
Mauritius finally got its
islands back after 60 years.
But here's what
didn't make the headlines.
The day before the
meeting that started all this,
a British official wrote a memo.
September 22nd, 1965.
His exact words.
"The object is to frighten him with hope.
Hope that he might get independence.
Fright lest he might not unless he is
sensible about the detachment of the
Chagos Archipelago."
The prime minister who
signed the 2025 deal,
his father was the man sitting across
from Harold Wilson in 1965,
being told to hand over those islands or
forget about independence.
60 years later, the son gets them back.
Sort of.
Because the two thousand
people Britain deported,
they're still not allowed to go home.
And Mauritius agreed to keep it that way.
So, what made these islands worth
threatening a
country's independence over?
Diego Garcia sits in the
middle of the Indian Ocean,
within striking
distance of the Persian Gulf.
South Asia, East Africa,
one of the best
natural harbors in the world.
By the 1960s, the Pentagon was watching
colonies become independent nations.
Nations that didn't always want American
bases on their soil.
They needed somewhere remote, somewhere
without political complications.
The phrase "exclusive control without
local inhabitants" is
from the planning documents.
The goal wasn't just a military base.
It was a base with no
voters, no journalists,
no one who might ask
questions at the United Nations.
There was just one problem.
About 1,500 people already lived there.
The Chagossians had been on
those islands for generations.
Descendants from enslaved and indentured
laborers with their own distinct culture.
So, Britain decided
to solve that problem.
First on paper, then in reality.
September 23rd, 1965.
The morning after that memo was written,
Harold Wilson met with
Seewoosagur Ramgoolam,
the premier of Mauritius at
Lancaster House in London.
And Wilson made the situation clear.
The premier and his colleagues could
return to Mauritius,
either with independence or without it.
That is a direct quote
from the meeting notes.
"Give us the islands or
you don't become a country."
Now, think about what's happening here.
Ramgoulam isn't negotiating as the leader
of an independent nation.
He is a colonial subject, sitting across
from the government,
that still controls his
country, being told what to do.
The ICJ would later apply what they
called "heightened
scrutiny" to this moment.
Their conclusion?
Britain's so-called consent from
Mauritius was not based on
the free and genuine expression
of the will of the people concerned.
Britain paid £3 million.
And on November 8th, 1965,
three years before Mauritius
would even become independent,
the UK passed the British
Indian Ocean Territory Order.
Using an archaic royal prerogative, no
parliamentary vote required.
They carved out the Chagos Archipelago
and created a brand new colony.
The paperwork was done, now they just had
to empty the islands.
The deportation happened in
stages and it was calculated.
The only way between Chagos
and Mauritius was by cargo ship.
So, starting in 1969,
Chagossians who left the islands to visit
family, for example,
found that they couldn't come back.
Their work contracts had expired.
The ship wouldn't take them.
Rita Bancoult was one of them.
A steamship company
representative told her directly,
"Your island has been sold.
You will never go there again."
Then the supplies started drying up.
Less food, less medicine.
The message wasn't subtle.
Leave or starve.
Those who stayed got it clearer.
Chagossians reported being told they'd be
bombed or shot if they refused to go.
And then there were the dogs.
Before the final deportations,
British agents rounded
up Chagossians' pets.
Hundreds of dogs, herded
them into a sealed shed
and ran exhaust fumes from military
vehicles into the building.
They gassed them and
then burned the bodies.
The families waiting to be
deported watched it happen.
Between 1967 and 1973,
somewhere between
1,500 and 2,000 Chagossians
were left on docks in
Mauritius and the Seychelles.
No housing arranged,
no jobs and no support.
One survivor put it this way,
"It's as if I was pulled from
my paradise to put me in hell."
For decades Mauritius pushed
this through international law.
And in 2019, they got their ruling.
I went through the ICJ opinion.
All 56 pages.
The language isn't ambiguous.
13 judges to one found that Britain's
decolonization of Mauritius
was not lawfully completed
when they carved out Chagos.
The court's exact words,
"The United Kingdom's continued
administration of the Chagos Archipelago
constitutes a wrongful act
entailing the international
responsibility of that state."
Now, to be fair to the UK position,
and I want to present the strongest
version of their argument,
Diego Garcia isn't just any base.
B-52s flew from that atoll during the
Afghanistan invasion.
Prepositioned ships
supplied the Gulf War.
The facility supports GPS,
nuclear test monitoring and
counter-piracy operations.
Defence experts call it
the single most
important military facility
between the
Mediterranean and the Pacific.
And the one dissenting
judge, Joan Donoghue,
made a serious legal argument.
She said this was a
bilateral sovereignty dispute.
And by ruling on it,
the ICJ was circumventing Britain's right
to refuse judicial settlement.
In her words,
"The court's decision undermines the
integrity of the
court's judicial function."
But here's the
problem with that argument.
The ICJ didn't treat this
as a simple land dispute.
An obligation owed to the entire
international community.
And when 116 countries
voted for Britain to withdraw,
and only 6 countries they voted against,
bilateral dispute doesn't
quite describe it anymore.
London's response.
"The UK representative said Britain had
no doubt about our sovereignty
and dismissed the ruling as
merely an advisory opinion.
The six-month deadline came and went.
Britain stayed.
Nothing changed.
Until 2025, May 22nd, 2025,
Britain finally signs over sovereignty.
Mauritius gets its territory back.
Decolonization complete.
Not quite, because when you read the
treaty, it's more complicated.
And this is where Mauritius
deserves some scrutiny too.
Diego Garcia, the island with the base,
the whole reason any of this happened,
stays under US-UK control for 99 years,
with an option to extend for another 40,
and potentially after that.
Britain pays Mauritius
about £101 million per year,
over the full term,
roughly £3.4 billion.
But here's what
doesn't make the headlines.
The Chagossians, the people
who were actually deported,
weren't at the table.
A UK spokesperson confirmed they could
not be part of the negotiations
as they were conducted on a
state-to-state basis.
Two governments
deciding the future of islands
that belonged to
neither of them originally,
and the people who lived
there, they were not invited.
And when you read the treaty,
there it is in black and white.
Mauritius can resettle
Chagossians on the other islands,
but Diego Garcia, the island their
families were removed from,
is explicitly excluded for 99 years.
This is where the story gets
uncomfortable for everyone.
The UK committed the original wrong.
The deportation, the ICJ
called it a wrongful act.
The UK itself now admits
it was shameful and wrong.
But Mauritius agreed to this deal.
They accepted the 99-year exclusion.
They took the £3.4 billion
and they signed away the Chagossians'
right to return to
Diego Garcia for a century.
In June 2025,
UN human rights experts put out a
statement saying the agreement
"fails to guarantee and protect the
rights of the Chagossian people,
including their right to
return to Diego Garcia."
There's a £40 million
trust fund for the Chagossians.
But as critics point out,
there's no guarantee that fund will
actually be controlled by Chagossians.
The Chagossian
community itself is divided.
Olivier Bancoult of the Chagos Refugee
group called it a "historic day".
But other groups like
Chagossian Voices opposed the deal
because it doesn't include
the full right of return.
Legal analysts note the resettlement
clause is in substance declaratory.
It doesn't actually
secure the right to return.
It just says Mauritius is free to
implement a program.
That's not exactly the same thing.
Diego Garcia remains exactly what the
planning documents
called for 60 years ago.
Exclusive control
without local inhabitants.
There's something almost
poetic about the Ramgoolam story.
In 1965, Harold Wilson sat across from
Seewoosagur Ramgoolam
and told him, "Give us these islands or
you won't get independence."
60 years later, Navin Ramgoolam signed a
treaty that formally gets them back.
But look at what actually changed.
In 1965, Britain controlled the islands.
The Chagossians couldn't go home.
In 2025, Mauritius
controls the islands on paper.
Britain still controls Diego Garcia.
The Chagossians still can't go home.
The UK calls it making amends.
Mauritius calls it a great victory.
But neither government asked the
Chagossians what they wanted.
The flag over Diego
Garcia will change eventually.
The base stays.
And until the people who were born on
those islands can
decide their own future,
you have to ask, "Is this decolonization
or is it just a
rebranded lease with better PR?"