Nick Fuentes makes a lot of
claims about the Holocaust.
Here's a telegram Nazi
officials sent each other in 1943.
1.27 million people
deported to death camps,
by camp, by date, in
their own encrypted message.
Tucker Carlson gave
Fuentes a two-hour interview.
Millions of views amid backlash.
Tucker never challenged
Fuentes on any of this.
Look, this isn't about winning arguments.
When Fuentes gets 4 million views
spreading false claims,
people believe him.
He makes two claims I'm
going to fact-check today.
1. There's no physical
evidence of Holocaust deaths.
2. The founding fathers
attacked the British first,
making them the aggressors,
just like the people who stormed the
Capitol on January 6th.
Different topics, but same method.
Ignore the primary
sources, rewrite the timeline,
and make extremism look justified.
Here's the pattern.
Both claims erase documentary evidence
that contradicts his politics.
The Nazi bureaucracy that
documented their own genocide,
and the founders' 15
months of failed diplomacy
before declaring independence.
Let's start with the Holocaust denial.
Then we'll get to the founding fathers.
January 11, 1943.
I'm reading directly from the
declassified telegram.
National Archives,
UK, reference HW 16/23.
The Nazis encrypted this message.
British intelligence decoded it in 2000.
One year, four camps,
deportation arrivals.
Belzec, more than 400,000.
Sobibor, more than 100,000.
Treblinka, more than 700,000.
Majdanek, more than 24,000.
In total, more than 1 million people.
Now, wait, this telegram tracks
deportations, not dead directly.
It's a logistics document.
Train arrivals at camps.
But here's why this is
evidence of genocide.
Treblinka, Sobibor and Belzec were part
of Aktion Reinhardt,
the Nazi code name for
exterminating Polish Jews.
Not labor camps, not transit
camps, pure killing centers.
In 1943, Himmler ordered
these camps dismantled.
Buildings torn down, mass
graves exhumed and burned,
trees planted over the sites.
Why destroy a transit camp?
If you're just moving people through,
you don't bulldoze the
evidence and plant forests.
Post-war excavations found
mass graves, cremation pits,
personal belongings from hundreds of
thousands of victims.
No barracks, no infrastructure for
housing millions of people.
So here's the question
deniers can't answer.
If 1.2 million people were just
relocated, where are they?
Where are the survivor testimonies of
millions being resettled in the east?
The Höfle telegram survived because
British intelligence intercepted it.
The camps didn't because
the Nazis destroyed them.
Keep these numbers in your head.
1.2 million people, one
year, four death camps.
April 2025, Fuentes tweets,
"David Irving did it better."
David Irving convicted Holocaust denier.
The British court ruled he deliberately
misrepresented historical evidence.
In 2019, Fuentes made a specific claim
about Holocaust math.
He said 15 ovens couldn't cremate 6
million people in five years.
The Nazis kept receipts for that too.
Remember Fuentes' claim, no physical
evidence, people died, just deportations.
But the Nazis didn't
just track deportations.
They tracked deaths as well.
In 2019, Fuentes said 15 ovens working
24-7 for five years
can't cremate 6 million.
Maybe 200 to 300 thousand cookies.
Let's see what the Nazi
paperwork actually says.
The Nazis commissioned a
professional statistician.
March 23, 1943, SS statistician Richard
Korherr to Heinrich Himmler.
Official title, the final
solution to the Jewish question.
Here's where it gets damning.
The report uses a euphemism.
"S.B.
Sonderbehandlung, special treatment."
This was Nazi code for killing.
The Korher report records over 1.8
million Jews given special treatment
through December 1942.
They knew they were documenting mass
murder and they hid it
in bureaucratic language.
That's long before the war even ended.
Fuentes said maybe 300 thousand total.
This is four times that in 12 months.
Fuentes says 15 ovens.
The blueprints say otherwise.
Auschwitz-Birkenau had
52 incineration chambers.
Called muffles.
Not 15.
52.
And here's where it
gets even more damning.
The Nazis didn't just count deaths.
They reported them up
the chain to Himmler.
To the people making decisions.
Fuentes based his entire Holocaust math
on a number he made up.
The Nazi blueprints prove him wrong.
But here's what's really important.
Most victims weren't
even cremated at Auschwitz.
The Einsatzgruppen, mobile killing units,
shot over a million
Jews in Eastern Europe.
They documented this.
With daily reports sent to Berlin.
October 7, 1941.
Report number 106.
Babi Yar ravine, Kiev.
33,771 Jews killed.
September 29 to 30.
Two days.
This wasn't hidden.
It was a routine report
filed with Berlin headquarters.
Location.
Date.
Method.
Body count.
These were direct killing reports.
Not euphemisms.
Not coded language.
Just the numbers.
All dismissible, apparently.
From what we've seen in
the actual Nazi records.
Not the summaries, but the originals.
The pattern's undeniable.
They track their victims with
bureaucratic precision.
Deportation logistics.
Death statistics.
Hidden in euphemisms.
That's just what the documents show.
The Treblinka, Sobibor and Belzec camps.
The ones in the Höfle Telegram.
Used mass graves and open air burning.
No ovens.
Witness testimony from Nazi guards.
Perpetrator confessions
and forensic evidence.
Fuentes claims there's
no physical evidence.
You just saw five Nazi documents.
Deportation records.
Statistical reports.
Blueprints.
Killing reports.
All from the perpetrators themselves.
The method doesn't fail.
The denial does.
The evidence shows an industrial
bureaucracy designed to
kill and document millions.
Now let's look at his second claim.
You might be wondering why he does this.
Because acknowledging it means his entire
framework collapses.
Fuentes has also claimed the Founding
Fathers attacked the British before
declaring independence.
Making them the aggressors.
Here's why this matters.
If the Founders shot first, they were
rebels who chose violence.
And if they could overthrow a government,
so could anyone else who
thinks they're oppressed.
January 6th defendants have literally
cited the Founding Fathers in court.
Claiming the same right to attack their
government after an election they lost.
But the timeline
completely destroys this argument.
Let's check the dates.
April 1774.
First Continental Congress
petitions King George for redress.
April 19, 1775.
Lexington and Concord.
British troops fire first.
Colonists return fire.
July 5th, 1775.
Olive Branch petition.
I'm reading directly from the document.
You can see it in the National Archives.
To the King's most excellent majesty.
We, your majesty's faithful subjects.
Look at that language.
Faithful subjects.
This was written three months after
Lexington and Concord.
After British troops fired on colonists.
And they're still
claiming loyalty to the King.
They're literally begging
for peace after being shot at.
The Kings rejected it.
And in August 23, 1775, King George
declares the colonies an
open and avowed rebellion.
Only then, nearly a
year after fighting began,
did the Continental
Congress vote for independence.
July 4, 1776.
In every stage of these oppressions, we
have petitioned for
redress in the most humble terms.
All repeated petitions have been answered
only by repeated injury.
They didn't attack first.
They exhausted every
peaceful option for 15 months.
The documentary evidence proves the
founders reluctance.
Fuentes' claim erases
15 months of diplomacy.
So let me bring it
back to where we started.
The Höfle Telegram, the Korherr Report,
Auschwitz Blueprints,
Einsatzgruppen Reports.
The Holocaust happened.
About 6 million Jews were killed.
The perpetrators documented it.
Even when they tried to hide what they
were doing with coded language.
The founding fathers exhausted peaceful
options for 15 months
before declaring independence.
When Fuentes claims they attacked first,
he erases the Olive Branch Petition.
The King's proclamation.
The whole timeline.
Both claims, Holocaust denial and January
6 justification,
erased documentary evidence.
So when Fuentes gets millions of views
saying "no evidence",
you now know what he's ignoring.
Nazi deportation records showing 1.2
million sent to death camps in one year.
Orders to destroy those
camps and hide the evidence.
Statistical reports using special
treatment as code for mass murder.
Einsatzgruppen reports documenting more
33,771 killed in two days.
That's not revisionism.
That's just lying.
If this kind of evidence-based
fact-checking is
valuable to you, subscribe.