For 200 years, standard history books
have repeated the same fact.
Christians placed Christmas on December
25th to override the pagan
festival of Sol Invictus,
the birthday of the unconquered sun.
It's a neat story and
it makes strategic sense.
It's become what one historian calls
"historical folklore".
But there's just one
massive problem with it.
When you actually check the primary
sources, the ancient Roman
calendars, the church records,
the documentary evidence,
the timeline doesn't match.
The earliest written evidence for a Roman
festival of Sol Invictus
on December 25th, 354 AD.
The earliest written evidence for
Christians celebrating
Christmas on December 25th, also
354 AD.
Same year, same document, same city.
And here's the crux, that ancient pagan
festival, it's actually no older than the
Christian one.
They appear in the exact same Roman
calendar, the Chronography of 354.
The recent scholarship is now suggesting
the direction of
borrowing might be backwards.
As historian C.P.E.
Nothaft wrote in 2012, it's altogether
possible to turn the tables
and assume that a supposedly
ancient festival of Sol was rediscovered
by pagan authorities in
response to the appropriation
of the winter solstice by Christianity.
The pagans may have been copying the
Christians, not the other way around.
So that's all the evidence, the document,
the dates and the
math that might actually
explain why Christmas
landed on December 25th.
Everything we know on December 25th in
ancient Rome comes down to
one document, the Chronography
of 354.
And calling it a
calendar doesn't do it justice.
This was a luxury illustrated almanac,
one of the most
expensive books produced in the
ancient world.
The calligrapher, Furius Dionysius
Philocalus, was the most
famous artist of his era, who
later carved
inscriptions for Pope Damasus.
The commissioner, a wealthy Christian
aristocrat named Valentinus.
Now here's what makes
this document so important.
It contains both entries for December
25th, the pagan one and the
Christian one, but they're
not entirely in the same section.
The pagan entry appears in the civil
calendar, the official
Roman lists of state festivals.
It reads "N INVICTI CM XXX",
translation "birthday of the
unconquered one, 30 chariot
races ordered".
The Christian entry appears in a
completely separate section
called the Depositio Martyrum,
the burials of the martyrs.
It reads "VIII kal. Ian. natus Christus
in Betleem Iudeae",
translation "December 25th,
Christ was born in Bethlehem of Judea".
And here's why this matters.
The pagan entry is in the
official state calendar.
It's like holidays,
games, imperial celebrations.
The Christian entry is in a private list
of commemorations for the Roman church.
By 354, Christmas wasn't some massive
public festival competing with Sol.
It was still an internal church
commemoration filed alongside
the burial dates of martyrs.
But here's the detail that recent
historians have focused on.
That pagan entry is weird.
Out of 63 race days in the entire
Chronography, 59 of them feature 24
chariot races, the standard
Roman number.
December 25th is one of
the only four exceptions.
It has 30, and it's the only race in the
calendar where the number
of races isn't a multiple
of 12.
Even stranger, it's the only birthday
entry in the entire
calendar that doesn't name the
deity.
Every other Natalis says "birthday of
Mars" or "birthday of Hercules".
This one just says
"birthday of the unconquered one".
No name.
Steven Hijmans, the Dutch historian who
first noticed this,
argues these anomalies suggest
the December 25th Sol festival was not
some ancient tradition.
It might have been a late, inconsistent
addition to the calendar.
What about Emperor Aurelian?
Everyone says he established the Sol
Invictus festival on
December 25th in 274 AD.
On December 25th in 274 AD.
But here's what
Aurelian actually did in 274.
He built a magnificent temple to Sol in
the Campus Martius.
He created a new college of priests
called the Pontifices Solis.
And he established quadrennial games in
honor of the sun god.
But here's what the sources don't say.
There is no explicit evidence that
Aurelian instituted
anything on December 25th.
No date on a coin and
no date in the decree.
According to Hijmans' analysis of the
Chronography, Aurelian's games, the
Agon Solis, were almost
certainly held in October, October 19th
to the 22nd to be precise.
The final day featured 36 chariot races,
the highest number of the entire year.
That's 36 races in
October versus 30 in December.
So if Aurelian's major celebration was in
October, where did the
December 25th festival
come from?
Hijmans' controversial conclusion.
The December 25th entry might be later
than we think, possibly
even later than the Christian
adoption of the date.
Nothaft summarizes this.
Hijmans is able to show that the idea of
Christmas being preceded
by a popular and important
feast dedicated to the sun god is to a
considerable extent founded on
anachronisms and a view
of Roman religion that rests on 19th
century constructs
rather than hard facts.
In other words, the story we've all heard
that there was this
massive ancient sun festival
that Christians strategically hijacked,
that story was largely
invented by 19th century
scholars.
The primary sources don't support it.
So if Christians didn't borrow December
25th from the pagans,
where did the date actually
come from?
To answer that, we don't look at the sun,
we look at their math calendar.
There's a theory historians call the
Calculation Hypothesis,
and it works like a code.
Early Christians reverse engineered the
date of Christ's birth
using a strange piece of
logic.
The logic works something like this.
Early Christians believed that perfect
lives must be whole
numbers, no fractions.
The saviour must live an exact number of
years, dying on the same
calendar day he was conceived.
They calculated the death of Christ as
March 25th, the spring
equinox in the Julian calendar.
This was also considered
the first day of creation.
So if Christ died on March 25th, and
perfect lives end on the
same day they begin, then
Christ must have been
conceived on March 25th too.
Now add 9 months for a
perfect human gestation.
March 25th plus 9
months equals December 25th.
That's not my interpretation, that's what
Saint Augustine
explicitly wrote in De Trinitate.
Therefore he is believed to have been
conceived on the 25th of
March upon which day also he
suffered.
But he was born, according to
tradition, upon December 25th.
The Christians didn't need a pagan
festival to land on
December 25th, the math got them
there independently.
Now to be fair to the pagan borrowing
theory, the coincidence is remarkable.
March 25th is the spring equinox,
December 25th is the winter solstice.
Both are astronomically significant dates
that would matter to any
ancient culture watching
the sky.
So even if Christians calculated the date
internally, the
symbolic power of the solstice,
the return of the light, almost certainly
enhanced the resonance
of celebrating Christ's
birthday on that day.
The question isn't whether solar
symbolism mattered, it's
whether there was a major
competing festival to strategically
displace.
It's whether there was a major competing
festival to strategically displace.
And on that specific question, the
evidence is surprisingly thin.
There's one more piece of evidence that
suggests Christmas might
be older than the standard
narrative allows, and it
comes from an unlikely source.
A heretical sect that hated Rome.
In 311 AD, that's 43 years before our
Chronography, a rigorous Christian group
called the Donatists
split from the mainland
church in North Africa.
And here's why that matters.
When groups split from a parent body,
they typically carry with
them the traditions that
existed before the split.
A century later, around 410 AD, St.
Augustine wrote a sermon
attacking the Donatists for
their lack of unity
with the universal church.
With good reason have the heretical
Donatists never wished to
celebrate this day, Epiphany,
with us.
They neither love unity, nor are they in
communion with the Eastern church where
that star appeared.
Augustine explicitly attacks the
Donatists for skipping
Epiphany, January the 6th.
But here's what he doesn't say.
He doesn't attack them
for skipping Christmas.
Historians like Thomas Talley argue this
silence is significant.
Augustine was a meticulous polemicist who
looked for every
opportunity to highlight Donatist
divergence.
If they had been skipping Christmas, he
almost certainly would have mentioned it.
The inference?
Donatists were probably celebrating
Christmas on December 25th,
which means the feast must
have existed in North Africa before 311
AD, decades before the
Chronography, and before
Constantine had any
influence on the church calendar.
This matters because the standard
narrative says Constantine and his
successors established
December the 25th as a strategic move to
compete with Sol
Invictus in the 4th century.
But if Christmas already existed in North
Africa during the
Great Persecution, before
Constantine even converted, that
narrative falls apart.
So let's put all of this together.
243 AD.
Christian chronographers are already
using March 25th as a
fixed point for calculating
Christ's life.
They get the birthday wrong, March 28th,
but the method is established.
274 AD.
Aurelian reforms the Sol cult, he builds
a temple, and creates priests.
He establishes games in October.
300-311 AD.
The Donatist argument suggests Christmas
may have already existed in North Africa.
Early 4th century.
The Anonymous Christian Treatise
completes the March 25th
plus 9 months calculation,
landing on December 25th.
336 AD.
The source material for the
Chronography's martyr list is compiled.
The first verified date
for Christmas in Rome.
354 AD.
The Chronography records both traditions.
The first time we see December 25th Sol
Festival in any official document.
Notice the timeline.
The earliest verified evidence for the
Christian calculation
predates the earliest verified
evidence for any major
Sol festival on that date.
That's why Nothaft suggests that we
might need to turn the tables entirely.
The December 25th Sol Festival, with its
anomalous 30 races and
missing deity name, might not
be an ancient
tradition Christians copied.
It might be a pagan
reaction to a Christian feast.
Now I want to be careful here.
We can't prove the
pagans copied Christians.
The Chronography shows both traditions
existing simultaneously in 354 AD.
And we can't
definitively say which came first.
But here's what Steven Hijmans, the
Dutch historian, concluded.
The December 25th Sol entry looks like a
late politically motivated insertion.
The 30 races instead of 24.
The missing deity name.
The lack of any earlier documentation.
His theory, by the mid 4th century
Christianity was growing.
Constantine had converted and pagan
authorities, watching the
church gain cultural ground,
may have rediscovered an old solar
tradition and scheduled it
on December 25th, specifically
to compete.
In other words, the ancient sun festival
wasn't ancient at all.
It was a counter move.
We can't prove this
definitively, but we can say this.
The confident claim that Christians stole
December 25th from a
popular ancient sun festival?
That claim has no
documentary support before 354 AD.
The narrative isn't ancient history.
It's 19th century scholarship.
What Nothaft calls 19th century
constructs rather than hard facts.
So let me bring this
back to where we started.
Every December you hear the same story.
Christians were struggling to convert
pagans, so they just
borrowed the date from a massive
sun festival.
It's a neat narrative, it sounds
strategic, and for two
centuries historians repeated
it as fact.
But when you check the primary sources,
that evidence doesn't support that story.
There's no proof of a major December 25th
Sol festival before Christians were using
the date.
The math that gets Christians to December
25th is internally consistent and doesn't
require a pagan festival to copy.
And recent scholarship is increasingly
skeptical of the entire
pagan takeover narrative.
The evidence for a solar cult in late
antiquity is commonly
exaggerated to the point that
Roman religion is sometimes portrayed as
centering on Sol in an almost
monotheistic fashion.
The real story isn't a
simple tale of cultural theft.
It's a fascinating intersection of
theological math, Roman record keeping
and scholarly assumptions
that went unquestioned for centuries.
So the next time somebody confidently
tells you that Christmas
is just rebranded paganism,
ask them for the primary source.
Because the dates don't match.