Open a map of Central America, you see
Belize, a small country
on the Caribbean coast.
Now open a Guatemalan map.
Belize disappears, instead
you see Tere Toria de Belize.
Guatemala claims this
entire country as their own.
Both sides point to an 1859
treaty to prove who's right.
So, I read that treaty.
Guatemala says it's void
because Britain violated it.
But the treaty itself doesn't make the
boundary conditional on
Britain's obligations.
So who's telling the truth?
Right now the International Court of
Justice is deciding
whether Belize should even exist.
Oral hearings are in 2026.
The ruling is expected for 2027.
And there is oil involved, potentially
billions of barrels in the
wider region, with disputed
offshore zones in play.
Here's what the 1859
treaty actually says.
Article 7.
Britain agreed to help build the cart
road from Guatemala City
to the Caribbean coast.
Britain never built the road.
Guatemala says the border is void.
Britain says the border
is permanent regardless.
So how did we get here?
Spain claimed this territory since the
1494 Treaty of Tordesillas.
Britain started logging in the 1600s.
For 150 years, Spain tried to expel
British loggers, attacking
settlements in 1717, 1730,
1754 and 1779.
Spain lost the Battle of St. George's Cay
in 1798 and stopped
seriously contesting British
presents.
Spain signed three treaties with Britain.
In 1763, 1783 and finally in 1786.
The 1786 treaty set Britain's southern
limit at Sibun River.
Britain could log, but
Spain kept sovereignty.
Then in 1821, Central America declared
independence from Spain.
After 18 years of civil wars and chaos,
Guatemala finally emerged as an
independent republic
in 1839.
They claimed to inherit
all Spanish sovereignty.
But Britain kept pushing south, way past
that Sibun River limit,
all the way down to the
Sartoon River, about
60 miles further south.
Guatemala protested.
Britain ignored them.
Then in 1859, everything became urgent.
The 1850 Clayton-Bulwer Treaty with the
United States said Britain
couldn't grab new Central
American territory after 1850.
But Britain had already
pushed past their limits.
Guatemala meanwhile
faced an existential threat.
An American mercenary named William
Walker had made himself
president of Nicaragua in
1856, backed by American investors.
Guatemala genuinely
believed they were next.
They needed British weapons and backing
or they could be
conquered by Walker's private
army.
Charles Lennox Wyke, British diplomat,
arrives in Guatemala.
He meets Pedro da Icesina,
Guatemala's foreign minister.
They signed a treaty in 23 days.
For context, Wyke's boundary treaties
with Nicaragua and Honduras took months.
This one took three weeks.
Look at what just happened.
The 1786 treaties had Britain's southern
limit at the Sibun River.
But Britain had pushed 60 miles further
south to the Sarsutun River.
This new treaty recognizes that
unauthorized expansion.
Guatemala legally recognized British
control over territory Britain
had taken without permission.
They signed because they were desperate
for protection from Walker.
Notice this specific
phrase in the treaty.
Boundaries that existed previous to and
on the first day of January 1850.
That date isn't random.
By dating the boundary to January 1st
1850, the day before the
Clayton-Bulwer treaty banned
new acquisitions,
Britain could tell Washington.
We're not acquiring new territory.
We're just recognizing
boundaries that already existed.
This boundary line runs right through
Kzunontunich, a Maya
archaeological site with a 100-foot
pyramid.
The Maya built this around 800, a
thousand years before this treaty.
When Wyke and Icesina signed in 1859,
there were two European
powers carving up lands
the Maya had built civilizations on.
Were any Maya leaders consulted?
No.
Article 7.
The two parties will use their best
efforts for establishing
the easiest communication
between the Atlantic and Pacific oceans.
They will contribute towards the
construction of a cart road.
This wasn't just any road.
Guatemala had Pacific ports
with almost no Atlantic access.
Their Caribbean coastline
was tiny and underdeveloped.
All their exports to Europe had to go the
long way around through
Mexico or take incredibly
slow mountain routes.
A direct road to the Caribbean would cut
shipping times in half.
A British surveyor estimated 157 miles
through dense jungle,
costing around 145 pounds, around
18 million in today's money.
What the Maya understood
this road as compensation.
They were giving up their claim to a
massive chunk of territory.
In exchange, they would get
infrastructure that would
transform their economy.
So in 23 days, Britain got legal
recognition for territory
they'd expanded into without
permission.
Guatemala got the
promise of infrastructure.
And the Maya, who'd lived on this land
for millennia, got nothing.
Years went by and Britain built nothing.
Colonial conflicts in
India and China took priority.
The road was expensive and would help
Guatemala, but offer Britain nothing.
So Britain just didn't do it.
In 1862, Britain declares
the territory a crown colony.
Officially a colony now,
not just a logging settlement.
Still, no road.
August 1863.
Britain and Guatemala try again.
New deal.
Britain would pay 50,000 pounds, about 6
million today, barely a
third of what the road would
cost.
And Guatemala would build the road
themselves with their own money.
Britain ratified it immediately.
But Guatemala's congress delayed, missing
the ratification deadline.
When they finally ratified it in 1865,
they added conditions
saying Britain still owed
the original road obligation.
Britain refused.
The deal collapsed.
No road was ever built, not even with
Guatemala's own money.
But here's what Britain did do.
As early as 1860 and 1861, they surveyed
and marked the boundary
line with stone monuments,
exactly like Article 1 required.
Then, in 1867 and 1869, they sent
diplomatic notes,
basically saying "We tried, we're
done, Article 7 is void."
No road, no money, no more negotiations.
From Britain's perspective, the boundary
provisions in Articles
1-6 were separate from
the road provision in Article 7.
The road was a nice
bonus that didn't work out.
The boundary?
That was permanent.
Guatemala saw it completely different.
The road was the point.
Essential compensation
for giving up territory.
No road meant no deal.
For 15 years Guatemala
tried to negotiate quietly.
But by 1884, Britain had formally
declared British Honduras
as a crown colony and clearly
wasn't budging.
That's when, on April 5th, 1884,
Guatemala sent their first
formal protest to Britain,
saying the 1859 treaty is void because
Britain violated it.
Britain didn't even respond.
For nearly a century,
the dispute just simmered.
Britain treated the boundary as settled.
Guatemala treated it as theft.
Then, on September 21st,
1981, beliefs become independent.
Guatemala refuses to recognize it.
This dispute extends to offshore waters
where oil companies are drilling.
Belize's onshore
production is tiny and collapsing.
But in 2024, after 19 years of nothing,
companies started
exploring offshore again.
Why?
Because whoever wins at the ICJ controls
those maritime zones
and the oil underneath.
Here's what nobody talks about.
Census data shows about 26 to 32 thousand
Maya people live in
the disputed areas today,
mostly Keiichi and Mopan
Maya in southern Belize.
That 1859 boundary line cut straight
through Maya territories
that had existed for centuries.
Villages that had been trading and
intermarrying for
generations suddenly found themselves
in different countries.
Throughout the 1800s,
thousands more Maya fled Guatemala.
Modern investors, including German
plantation owners, had taken
over massive coffee estates.
Guatemala's government was forcing Maya
communities to provide labor.
So they crossed the border they never
agreed to, looking for refuge from
systems that treated
them as property.
Today, the ICJ case is going to decide
these borders permanently.
How many Maya representatives are
involved in the case?
Zero.
Many communities still don't have legal
land titles from either government.
They're caught between two states that
both claim the land beneath their feet.
If Guatemala wins, Belize could lose
territory, lose maritime zones or get
forced into splitting
oil revenue.
If Belize wins, Guatemala's 165-year-old
claim ends permanently.
And dozens of other disputed colonial
borders around the
world, places like Kashmir and
Western Sahara,
they're all watching this.
Britain signed a treaty promising a road.
Britain never built the road.
Guatemala says the border is void.
Britain, in now Belize, says the border
is permanent regardless.
One country's occupied territory is
another country's homeland.
And 26,000 Maya people caught in the
middle never got a vote.