In March 2025, a new YouGov poll survey
asked Americans about the Middle Ages.
Here's what they found.
48% describe it as dark, 54% said
violent, and only 2% claim they actually
know much about the period.
So here's the question.
Were the Dark Ages really dark?
One side dismisses this as Hollywood myth.
The other insists the intellectual
collapse after Rome's fall was real.
Libraries burned.
Literacy vanished.
Europe went dark for 500 years.
I went to the modern academic sources.
Chris Wickham's Medieval Europe,
quantitative manuscript counts from
Buringh and Van Zanden,
Mayke de Jong's work on the Carolingians.
They're analyzing the actual manuscript
production data, the legal
codes from successor kingdoms,
and the charter documents that ordinary
people used for property transactions.
When you examine the evidence, both
extremes oversimplify
what actually happened.
And here's why this matters.
The poll shows that 51% of Americans say
that they learn medieval history from
movies, not historians.
That gap between popular belief and
academic reality, that's
what I'm trying to fix.
Before we can talk about whether literacy
collapsed, we need to ask
how high were we to begin with?
The assumption is always that classical
Rome was this intellectual utopia.
Everyone's reading Virgil, universal
education, scroll
libraries on every corner.
Reading from the sources on ancient
literacy, papyrus was
prohibitively expensive.
Unless you were a wealthy government or
maybe a temple running
your entire operation on
written documents just wasn't feasible.
Even at the peak, Athenian democracy in
the 4th century BCE,
here's what the evidence shows.
Citizens serving on juries got a little
ticket with their name on it.
You had to be able to read your own name,
maybe the date, but not
a complex legal decree.
The assembly functioned perfectly well
without every member
reading and writing complex prose.
Because what did it rely on?
Oral culture.
Literary texts, philosophy, poetry, they
were mainly disseminated orally.
You didn't read Plato yourself, you went
to a performance or a public reading.
And here's the critical distinction that
reframes the entire Dark Ages argument.
The massive use of writing by the
government does not equal universal
individual literacy.
Rome's writing served the
state, not ordinary citizens.
Rome was already operating on a highly
stratified system where
writing served the state and
a wealthy elite.
Most knowledge was still shared orally.
So when the Western Roman Empire
transitions in the 5th
century, it's not falling from
some 90% literate utopia.
It's transitioning from a system where
literacy was already
specialized, already limited and
already expensive.
So if the state collapses,
where does the writing go?
The traditional story demands chaos here.
Barbarians sack Rome, the lights go out,
all sophisticated government just ends.
But the sources reveal a story of
institutional adaptation.
Visigothic Spain?
Far from chaos, they maintained Roman
governmental style with
careful attention to legal form.
And here's the litmus test
for any functioning state.
Taxes.
The Visigoths kept tax
collection functional.
That's the institutional hallmark of a
surviving, structured state.
Lombard Italy operated on a different
model, but equally pragmatic.
The main function of their
assemblies was law and justice.
Appeals went all the way
up to the capital at Pavia.
And their laws show how
sophisticated this was.
King Liutprand's legislation includes this
incredibly specific law.
The penalty for a man who steals a
woman's clothes while she's
bathing in a river forcing
her to walk home naked.
His full weregild.
The blood price paid for killing someone.
The highest possible fine.
The same as if you'd killed him.
What does that tell us?
The law is designed to
prevent blood revenge.
By setting the highest penalty, the king
stops the victim's
family from seeking violent
retaliation which would
spiral into clan warfare.
This is tight, functional government
aimed at social cohesion.
The Franks found it so impressive they
borrowed these exact legal procedures.
Many of these barbarian
leaders were already Romanized.
Bilingual.
They adopted every functional element of
Roman administrative systems.
They weren't hordes
wiping the slate clean.
They were continuing Roman governance
under new management.
But the successor kingdoms
just built the foundation.
The Carolingians provided the ambition.
Under Charlemagne, learning and the
written word went from
being a functional tool for
administrators to being a fundamental
pillar of state identity.
His logic was simple.
If his priests couldn't read the liturgy
or scripture
accurately, how could his people
possibly be saved?
The sources define his aim at one key
Latin word, correctio,
correction or reform.
Establishing a collective moral framework for
the salvation of the
entire Frankish people.
And that intellectual drive immediately
translates into massive
expansion of administration.
Literacy became essential for the royal
bureaucracy, for maintaining
law, for social advancement.
The material output is astonishing.
Large scale production of law books,
capitularies, royal decrees covering
everything from church
discipline to military organization to
judicial procedures.
And we can quantify this.
Buringh and Van Zanden analyzed
manuscript production across Europe.
In the 6th and 7th centuries, the period
that most people
associate with the Dark Ages,
there were 24,191 manuscripts produced.
In the 8th and 9th centuries under the
Carolingians, 245,444 manuscripts.
That's a 915% increase.
The lights didn't go
out, they got brighter.
Think about the logistics.
Charlemagne's court was huge and often
itinerant, moving around.
How did they organize moving hundreds,
maybe thousands of people
without destroying local
communities they landed on?
Through written notice.
And then there's the diplomacy.
The sheer geographic scope completely
refutes any idea of a
dark, isolated Western Europe.
Charlemagne was receiving and sending
legates to Arabic rulers
in Spain, to the Danes, to
the Huns and most memorably he received
legates from the Abbasid
Caliph Harun al-Rashid in
Persia.
This included an elephant and a
water-powered automaton clock.
The palace chapel at Aachen was built
with columns carted
from Rome and Ravenna.
It was a physical symbol, a conscious
effort to link this new,
Frankish power directly
to the classical imperial Roman past.
Court poetry celebrated
Aachen as the new Athens.
The revival was completely intentional.
Crucially, and this is a huge point
against the Dark Ages
myth, this literacy wasn't
just for clergy.
Einhard, a layman from a minor
aristocratic family, he rose
to immense influence solely
because of his intellectual skill.
He was an advisor, he managed huge
building projects and
later wrote a seminal biography
of Charlemagne.
His entire career was built on his
written intellectual abilities.
And then there's Dhuoda, the wife of
aristocrat Bernard of Septimania.
She wrote a detailed handbook for her son
William, filled with
advice drawn from Christian
Latin literature from patristic sources.
The complexity and the sheer range of
literature she
synthesizes, it strongly suggests she
was fully educated,
probably at Aachen itself.
Which proves high level Latin literacy
existed among the
Carolingian aristocratic laity for
both men and women.
After Charlemagne dies, the intellectual
systems he created didn't vanish.
They diffused.
Monasteries like St. Gall provided what
the sources call an
"itinerant notarial service".
Scribes didn't just stay writing prayer
books, they traveled out
into surrounding communities
to provide professional written
documentation services
to non-monastic people.
Charters for gifts, sales, exchanges of
property, high stakes
transactions that cemented who
owned what land.
And the procedure shows how important the
document had become.
Witnesses in these transactions had to
confirm they saw the
document being written.
Their hands were physically
placed on the completed document.
It's a societal affirmation that the
written word now holds the
ultimate legal authority.
The written document had
become essential for ordinary life.
So let's be clear about what
the evidence actually shows.
1.
Classical Rome wasn't
universally literate.
It was already a highly stratified system
where writing served
elite functions and most
knowledge was shared orally.
2.
Successor kingdoms maintained sophisticated
legal and administrative systems.
They kept taxes, wrote complex laws and
continued Roman governance.
3.
The Carolingians launched a deliberate,
centrally driven cultural revolution.
They standardized scripts, produced
massive legal codes, trained
lay elites in Latin literacy
and used writing to guarantee justice.
Knowledge definitely became concentrated,
centered around
monasteries, cathedrals and
royal courts.
But it was deployed strategically to
build new Christian
states with sophisticated legal
structures.
The term "Dark Ages" fundamentally fails
to capture that reality.
If this changed how you think about the
Middle Ages, please subscribe.
There's more myth-busting coming.