On June 16th 2014, a farmer from Virginia
named Jeremiah Heaton planted
a flag in the African desert.
Why? To make his 7 year old
daughter Emily a princess.
He claimed 800 square miles of land
between Egypt and Sudan and called it the
Kingdom of North Sudan.
CNN, Time, Newsweek,
hundreds of outlets covered it.
Most of them treated it like
a cute human interest story.
But here's what almost
nobody explained. He wasn't crazy.
This was one of the only places on earth
besides Antarctica where you could even
try something like this.
Because Berthawil is one of the only
pieces of habitable land
that no country claims.
This isn't a disputed territory, it's not
a border conflict where
both sides claim the same land.
This is the opposite. Both Egypt and
Sudan actively reject it.
And here's the kicker, claiming Berthawil
would cost either Egypt or Sudan the land
that they actually want next door.
There's two pieces of
land between Egypt and Sudan.
Berthawil, 800 square miles of landlocked
desert, no water, no infrastructure,
economically worthless
compared to Hala'ip and...
The Hala'ip triangle, 8000 square miles,
10 times bigger with the Red Sea
coastline and oil potential.
And on top of that,
700,000 tons of manganese.
And here's the problem, because of how
the British drew the
borders, you can't claim both.
In 1899, Britain and Egypt signed the
Anglo-Egyptian Condominium Agreement.
The treaty says Sudan is defined as
territory south of the
22nd parallel of latitude.
Quite straightforward. A straight line
across the map at the 22nd parallel.
Under this border, Egypt gets Hala'ip and
Sudan gets Berthawil.
But three years later, the British
changed their minds.
On November the 4th, 1902, they created a
new administrative boundary.
Not a straight line this time. This one
was based on tribal use
and settlement patterns.
The Ababdah tribe graced in Berthawil, so
Britain assigned it to
Egyptian administration.
The Beja tribes in Hala'ip were tied to
Sudan, so they assigned that
to Sudanese administration.
Now, here's the problem. Two borders and
two completely different outcomes.
The 1899 border gives Egypt
Hala'ip the valuable coastline.
The 1902 border gives Sudan the Hala'ip.
Both countries want Hala'ip, so Egypt
claims the 1899 line.
Sudan claims the 1902 line. And
Berthawil? Neither will touch
it, because claiming Berthawil
means accepting the
border that gives away Hala'ip.
That's why Jeremiah Heaton
could just walk right in.
Two colonial borders. One paradox still
unresolved 70 years after independence.
So why don't they just
negotiate? The Hala'ip triangle.
8,000 square miles. Red Sea coastline
with manganese and possible oil.
In comparison, Berthawil has 800 square
miles of sand and no water.
One is worth fighting for, the other
isn't. Egypt and Sudan
both call it uninhabited.
Tell that to the thousands running
illegal gold mines there,
or the Ababda tribe who've
graced here for generations.
No permanent settlements, no
infrastructure, no government
services, but it's not empty.
And the Ababda? They weren't consulted in
1899. They weren't consulted in 1902.
Their grazing lands just became a
bargaining chip between two governments
that don't want them.
And the dispute over
Hala'ip? It's gotten violent.
In 1992, Sudan granted offshore
exploration rights to
a Canadian oil company.
Egypt objected. In 1994, Egyptian
military forces expelled Sudanese
officials from Hala'ip.
In 1995, there was an assassination
attempt on Egyptian President Mubarak.
Egypt blamed Sudan and strengthened
military control over Hala'ip.
By 2000, Sudan withdrew its forces. Egypt
has controlled the territory ever since.
So when Hinton showed up to claim
Berthawil, neither country cared.
His daughter had asked if
she could be a real princess.
In Hinton's own words, "Ain't nothing
more important than my
daughter's happiness,
and now she's got
everything she ever wanted."
He even got permission
from Cairo to make the trip.
Egypt let him drive through, plant his
flag, declare the Kingdom of North Sudan.
Why? Because Egypt
doesn't claim Berthawil.
Letting some American play
pretend costs them nothing.
And he's not alone. Many others have
tried to claim Berthawil.
A Russian radio operator declared it the
Kingdom of Middle-Earth in 2017.
An Indian businessman called
it Kingdom of Dixit in 2017.
Each one with flags, GPS
locks, and bold declarations.
Every claim has been ignored.
The United Nations hasn't recognized any
claimant as Berthawil's legitimate ruler.
Because in modern international law, you
can't just plant a
flag and create a country.
You need a permanent population, a
functioning government, and
recognition from other states.
Berthawil has none of those. So legally,
Emily is not a princess.
But the Hinton story going viral,
millions of views,
hundreds of news outlets,
that reveals something important.
We're fascinated by the idea of unclaimed
land, because almost
none of it exists anymore.
Every piece of habitable land on Earth is
claimed by some country.
Except for Berthawil. Four small pockets
along the Danube River.
But that's a
Croatia-Serbia border dispute.
And parts of Antarctica.
But the Antarctic Treaty System suspends
all of those claims.
That's it.
In a world of 8 billion people divided
into roughly 200 countries.
This is all that's left.
And Berthawil's unclaimed status?
That's a direct result
of European colonialism.
The British drew two borders.
The 1899 line ignored
where tribes actually lived.
It was just a straight line
for political convenience.
The 1902 line tried to fix this by
following tribal territories.
But it created a worse problem.
They drew one border
for political sovereignty,
and then another border for tribal
administration three years later.
They didn't think about what would happen
when Egypt and Sudan became independent.
And the consequences are
still playing out today.
Egypt controls Khalaib by military force.
Sudan still claims it diplomatically.
A 2020 Carnegie Endowment report found
that since Sudan's independence in 1956,
border relations with Egypt have been
characterized more by mutual suspicion
than by peaceful exchange.
And Berthawil is still unclaimed.
Still unwanted.
A colonial leftover that nobody wants to
touch because claiming it
means giving up Khalaib.
So when Jeremiah Heaton
planted that flag in 2014,
he wasn't just trying to make his
daughter a princess.
He was highlighting an absurdity.
800 square miles of land between two
countries that
neither country will claim.
Because admitting Berthawil is yours
means admitting Khalaib isn't.
The only land on earth nobody owns exists
because two countries are
fighting over the land next door.
And Berthawil isn't unique.
It's just the most visible example.
Across Africa and the Middle East,
colonial borders drawn a century ago
still fuel territorial disputes.
Think about the Western Sahara,
Somaliland, all those trade
lines cutting through the desert.
The difference?
Everyone wants those territories.
Berthawil is the only one nobody wants.
That's not just a legal curiosity.
That's a colonial border dispute that's
still unresolved 70
years after independence.
And it won't be the last one.
If this kind of evidence-based deep dive
into historical oddities is
your thing, please subscribe.