You've probably heard it a million times.
Sykes-Picot drew the Middle East borders.
ISIS cited it when they
bulldozed the Iraq-Syria border.
Kurdish independence
advocates point to it.
Analysts on Palestine
bring it up constantly.
And politicians love to say Britain and
France carved up the
Middle East with a ruler.
But guess what? They're all wrong.
I went through the original documents.
The actual Sykes-Picot text, the
Hussein-McMahon letters,
San Remo Records and
League of Nations archives.
And what I found, it's
not what we've been told.
Let's break it down.
People say this 1916
map drew the borders.
But look at the proof.
Or actually the lack of it.
Take Mosul.
Oil-rich, strategic, absolutely crucial.
Sykes-Picot put it in the French zone.
But it ended up in British Iraq.
10 years later.
After years of negotiations, oil company
deals and League of Nations Commission,
Iraq's borders finalized in 1926.
Syria-Palestine 1923.
Transjordan 1921.
Not 1916.
We're talking 10 to 15 years later.
And here's why that matters.
When we blame everything on one 1916 map,
we miss the actual story.
The decade of broken promises.
The oil deals.
The local resistance that changed things.
All of it gets erased.
Because here's what people forget.
These places already existed.
Look at this Ottoman map from 1893.
Three provinces.
Basra, Baghdad and Mosul.
And across them the
label, Al-Iraq Al Arabi.
Arab-Iraq.
Iraq wasn't invented by Europeans.
Neither was Syria.
These lined up with Ottoman provinces
like Damascus, Aleppo and Beirut.
So when Europeans showed up, they weren't
drawing on a blank map.
They were redrawing someone else's.
And that's where the real problem starts.
Because Britain didn't
just draw bad borders.
They made three
completely contradictory promises
to three different
groups about the same land.
July 14, 1915.
Sharif Hussein of Mecca writes to Britain
demanding a massive Arab kingdom.
Syria, Iraq, Arabia and even Palestine.
On October 24, 1915, the British High
Commissioner Henry McMahon replies.
And I'm quoting directly here.
"Subject to the above modifications,
Great Britain is prepared
to recognize and support
the independence of the Arabs in all the
regions within the limits
demanded by the Sharif of Mecca."
Now, those modifications
excluded some coastal areas.
Historians still argue about whether that
meant Palestine was in or out.
But the promise of Arab independence?
That was clear.
So that's promise number one.
Six months later, May 1916, Britain
secretly signs a deal with France.
The Sykes-Picot agreement.
They draw a diagonal
line from Acre to Kirkuk.
Blue zone.
France controls
coastal Syria and Lebanon.
Red zone.
Britain gets southern Iraq.
Area A, French influence.
Area B, British influence.
And the brown zone, Palestine, under
international administration.
The exact same lands they
just promised to Hussein.
That's promise number two.
And here's where it
gets really complicated.
November 23, 1915.
Seven months before
Sykes-Picot was even signed.
At a meeting in London, seven British
officials brief François Georges-Picot,
the French negotiator, on the promise
they'd already made to the Arabs.
And according to the official British
minutes of that meeting,
Picot says, "To promise the Arabs a large
state is to throw dust in their eyes.
Such a state will never materialize."
They knew the Arab promises were lies.
And they signed the agreement anyway.
Then comes November the 2nd, 1917.
Foreign Secretary Arthur Balfour writes
to Lord Rothschild saying,
"Britain supports the establishment in
Palestine of a national
home for the Jewish people."
Same Palestine, same land.
That's promise number three.
Three promises, two years,
one massive contradiction.
So if Sykes-Picot didn't
create the final borders, what did?
Well, it took 15 years.
A world war ending, oil being discovered,
local uprisings, and
endless diplomatic negotiations.
April, 1920.
The San Remo Conference.
The Allies formally assign mandates.
France gets Syria and Lebanon.
Britain gets Mesopotamia and Palestine.
But, and this is
crucial, the fine print says,
"Exact boundaries to be determined by the
principal Allied powers."
Translation, we'll figure it out later.
And later drags on for years.
Britain promises Iraq independence.
Then they find oil in Mosul.
Suddenly, independence means another
decade of British control
while they negotiate who
gets the oil concessions.
1922.
Britain and Ibn Saud sign a treaty
fixing the Iraq-Najd border.
1925-26.
A League of Nations commission spends
months investigating the Mosul question.
They hear testimony from local leaders,
examine ethnic composition,
consider economic factors, and
then award it to British Iraq.
Not because of self-determination,
but because Britain had better
infrastructure and oil development plans.
1932.
Iraq finally gains independence.
16 years after Sykes-Picot.
And that language of temporary control is
still being used today.
When Israel's defense
minister said in 2024,
they'd stay in Syrian territory until
another arrangement is found,
that's the exact same language Britain
used in Iraq a century ago.
An occupation with no end date,
waiting for conditions
that never quite materialize.
But here's what the
Europeans drew all the borders,
myth misses,
locals fought back
and sometimes they won.
August 10, 1920.
The Treaty of Sèvres tries to formalize
the Ottoman breakup,
carving up Turkey itself.
Turkey says no.
Ataturk leads the Turkish War of
Independence from 1919-1923,
defeating Greek,
Armenian, and French armies.
Then, on July 24, 1923, the Treaty of
Lausanne replaces Sèvres.
Turkey regains its land,
European powers back down.
That's not a line on a map,
that's a military
victory rewriting the map.
In Iraq, the 1920 uprising,
a massive revolt
against British occupation,
forces Britain to
completely rethink how they rule.
They installed Faisal ibn Hussein,
the same Arab leader who briefly ruled
Syria before the French expelled him as
King of Iraq.
The new monarchy looks independent,
but Britain still holds the real power.
The borders don't change,
but the governance does.
And that's still shaped by resistance.
These weren't just European lines on
paper that everyone accepted.
So, fast forward to 2014.
ISIS bulldozes the Iraq-Syria border,
declaring "We're erasing Sykes-Picot".
But that border was
finalized in 1923, not 1916.
Kurdish activists cite Sykes-Picot for
dividing Kurdistan across four countries.
Palestine experts point to it as the
origin of broken promises.
Syria analysts call it
the root of their civil war.
And look, they're not wrong that European
powers screwed things up.
The three
contradictory promises were real.
The disregard for
local populations was real.
But when we say one secret
map in 1916 created all this,
we're missing what actually happened.
It wasn't one map.
It was a decade plus of
negotiations driven by oil,
shaped by resistance and finalized
through commissions and
treaties that came years later.
And those contradictory promises?
Those were the real poison.
Not the specific lines,
but the intentional lies
to three different groups about who would
control the same land.
So, let's be clear about what the
evidence actually shows.
1. Britain made three conflicting
promises between 1915 and 1917.
Hussein-McMahon,
Sykes-Picot and Balfour.
The French negotiator himself said the
Arab state was being
thrown dust in their eyes.
They knew it was a lie.
2. The borders we have
today weren't fixed in 1916.
They came from 15 years
of negotiations, oil deals,
League of Nations
commissions and local resistance.
Mosul in 1926, Syria-Lebanon in 1923,
and Iraq independence in 1932.
3. Locals weren't passive.
Turkey fought and won.
Iraq and Syrian populations
resisted and forced changes.
Not always to borders, but to governance.
The final map wasn't
just what Europeans wanted.
When politicians today blame artificial
borders on Sykes-Picot,
they're repeating a century-old myth that
erases the actual history.
European powers did make
contradictory promises.
The borders do shape modern conflicts,
but they came from a long contested
process where oil, resistance and
geopolitics all played a role.
Not just one secret map.
If you want more evidence-based history
that breaks down what actually happened,
instead of what we've
been told, hit subscribe.
Thanks for watching,
see you in the next one.