This is a law that stripped French
citizens of their jobs, their rights and
their place in public life, based on
their grandparents' race.
It was written in French and if you don't
read French you've
probably never read it.
The United States Holocaust Memorial
Museum describes its provisions.
Yad Vashem summarizes them.
Academic books quote sections of it.
But a readable, clause-by-clause English
translation of the full text?
I couldn't find one, so I made one.
And then there's something else.
A draft of this law, covered in
handwritten annotations from the French
head of state himself.
Those annotations have never been
translated or walked through in English.
They proved he didn't just sign this law.
He personally made it worse.
They proved, but was not the hero that
most people make him out to be.
I'm going to show you both.
On October 3rd, 1940, the Vichy
government published the Statute des
Juifs, the Jewish Statute.
It created a racial
definition of who counted as Jewish.
It banned Jews from almost every position
of public influence.
And it applied those bans across the
entire French Empire.
For decades the official French position
was that Germany imposed this.
After the war, Vichy's own justice
minister, a man named
Joseph Barthélemy, said, and this
is a direct quote, "This legislation is
not a French initiative.
It is entirely of German origin."
The archives proved that was a lie.
We know this because of three things.
First, the armistice France signed with
Germany in June 1940
said nothing about Jews.
Historians Marrus and Paxton went through
both the German and French archives.
Their conclusion, close study of German
and French archives,
reveals no German demand
in 1940 that Vichy
adopt an anti-Jewish policy.
Second, France was already passing
anti-Jewish measures
before Germany issued anything.
In July 1940, they restricted public
service jobs to people
born of French fathers.
In August, they
restricted the medical profession.
In late August, they repealed the
Marchandeau law, the law that had made
anti-Semitic attacks
in the press illegal.
All of this before any
German ordinance on Jews.
And thirdly, when Germany finally did act
on September 27,
1940, what they did demand
was limited.
A census and property registration, only
in the occupied zone.
And they used a religious
definition of who was Jewish.
Six days later, France responded with
something far broader, a racial
definition, a full professional
purge applied across
the entire French empire.
France didn't just follow Germany.
France went further.
The first thing the law
does is define its target.
And the word it uses is
"race", not "religion".
"Race juive", the Jewish race.
If you had three Jewish grandparents, you
were counted as a Jew.
It didn't matter if you
were baptized Catholic.
It didn't matter if you'd
never set foot in a synagogue.
If you had two Jewish grandparents, you
could escape the definition.
Unless your spouse was Jewish, then you
were fully Jewish under the law.
And notice, the law never defines what
makes a grandparent Jewish.
The definition is circular.
That's not sloppy drafting.
A vague definition gave
authorities maximum discretion.
Marrus and Paxton again.
Vichy's "Statut des juifs" went further than
the German ordinance.
Whereas the German ordinance spoke only
of religion, the Vichy
law spoke openly of race.
Article 2 is the ban list.
And when you read it,
you understand the scale.
Jews were banned from head of state,
every court from the
Supreme Court down to the local
magistrate, every elected assembly, all
prefects, all police, all
diplomats, all colonial governors,
all military officers, all teachers, any
director of a company
receiving public money.
That's not a ban on a
few senior positions.
That's a systematic removal from every
institution that exercises
authority, shapes culture or
controls information.
By 1942, roughly 3,400 public servants
had been dismissed in mainland France,
another 2,500 in Algeria.
Article 5 bans Jews without condition or
reservation, from directing, managing or
editing any newspaper,
magazine or periodical.
Then cinema, directors, producers,
screenwriters, then radio.
No war hero exceptions.
No exemptions at all.
The only thing Jews could still publish
was scientific journals.
That one exception tells you everything
about the law's purpose.
A Jewish journalist isn't banned because
they're bad at their job.
They're banned because they shape what
French people think.
This is about controlling who tells
France its stories.
With one sentence, they extended the law
across the entire French empire.
In Morocco, 32 of 37 Jewish lawyers were
removed from the bar.
Four days after this statute, a separate
law stripped over
100,000 Algerian Jews of the
citizenship they'd held for 70 years.
But it didn't stop in North Africa.
French administrators applied this law
everywhere, including territories
thousands of miles from
the nearest German soldier.
In French Indochina,
they counted 140 Jews.
French West Africa, 110.
Martinique, 36.
Guadeloupe, 22.
Madagascar, 26.
There was no military requirement to
register 22 people in Guadeloupe.
There were no German
troops in Martinique.
This wasn't geopolitics.
This was administrative zeal.
Marrus and Paxton call this the
definitive proof that Vichy's
antisemitism was indigenous.
That's the law.
Now I want to show you something that was
hidden for 70 years.
In 2010, 70 years to the day after the
statute was signed, a
lawyer, a Nazi hunter named
Serge Klarsfeld, held a press conference
at the Memorial de la Shoah in Paris.
He had a typed draft of the statute,
stamped "DOCUMENT
CONFIDENTIEL", covered in handwritten
annotations.
Handwriting experts confirmed they
were Philippe
Pétain's, the head of the Vichy
state.
I have this document.
I have translated his notes.
The typed draft listed specific
educational administrators,
directors, inspectors, school
directors.
Pétain wrote in the margin "tout personnel
enseignant", all
teaching personnel, not just
the people who run the schools, every
teacher at every level.
The typed draft banned Jews
from specific named institutions.
Pétain added "toutes assemblées issues
de l'élection" all
assemblies arising from
elections, every municipal council, every
departmental council,
every elected body in
France and its empire.
The draft banned Jews
from the high courts.
Pétain extended it to "justices de paix",
the village magistrate courts, the lowest
level of French justice.
And then there's the
change that matters most.
The typed draft, already harsh, had a
protection clause,
condition A, read "être descendant
de Juifs nés français ou
naturalisés avant
l'année 1860" to
be a descendant of Jews born French or
naturalized before the year 1860.
That's an 80-year grandfather clause.
If your family had been French since
Napoleon III, you were protected.
These were France's most established,
most assimilated Jewish families.
Families who had been
French for generations.
Pétain drew a line
through the whole sentence.
With one pen stroke, he
erased 80 years of citizenship.
It didn't matter if your
great-grandfather fought for France.
If you fit the racial
definition, you were out.
Not a single annotation on
this document softened the law.
Every remark expanded who had targeted or
removed the protection.
He added professions.
He closed loopholes.
He erased the one clause that would
protect France's oldest Jewish families.
Klarsfeld noted "The main argument of
Pétain defenders was
to say that he protected
French Jews.
This argument has now fallen."
After the war, Charles de Gaulle, the
leader of the Free
French Resistance and France's
first post-war president, declared all of
Vichy's laws null and void.
His position was simple.
Vichy was never the real France.
The Republic had just been interrupted.
And if Vichy wasn't the real France, then
France bore no responsibility.
That was the official
position for 50 years.
It held until 1995.
Jacques Chirac, standing at the site
where French police had
arrested over 13,000 Jews
in 1942, said what no
French president had said before.
France, the home of the Enlightenment and
of the rights of
man, delivered those she
should have protected
to their executioners.
Not Vichy.
France.
I want to be fair about one thing.
75% of Jews living in
France survived the war.
That's a higher rate than almost any
other occupied country.
But that survival
wasn't because of this law.
It was because of ordinary French people
who chose to protect
their neighbors, despite
what their government was doing.
The law we just read
didn't protect anyone.
I've linked the full translation and the
original French text
in the description so
you can read the whole thing yourself.
That's what this series is trying to do,
translating historic
sources that were never
made accessible in English.
If you want to see more of these,
subscribe, there's a lot
more documents to translate.