In 1996, the Russian parliament declared
that the document ending
the Soviet Union was illegal.
In 2025, presidential adviser Anton
Kobiakov went even further.
The Soviet Union, he said,
never legally ceased to exist.
Today we're going to
examine that document.
The Belavezha Accords
and ask a simple question.
Was the end of the
Soviet Union actually legal?
Let's look at the evidence.
December 8th, 1991.
Three leaders meet in a
Belarusian hunting lodge.
They sign a single document.
Its preamble reads, "We, the Republic of
Belarus, the Russian
Federation and Ukraine,
as Founder States of the Union of Soviet
Socialist Republics and Signatories of
the Union Treaty of 1922,
hereby declare that the Union of Soviet
Socialist Republics, as a subject of
international law and
geopolitical reality,
no longer exists.
Article V promises to acknowledge and
respect each other's territorial
integrity and the
inviolability of existing borders.
Article XIV delivers the kill shot.
The activities of organs of the former
USSR in the territories of the states
members of the
Commonwealth are hereby terminated.
Three men, one document.
Was it legal?
The case against the
Accords is straightforward.
First, Soviet law already
had a secession process.
The 1990 secession law required a
five-year transition, a two-thirds
majority referendum,
minority veto rights and approval from
the Congress of People's Deputies.
The Belavezha
signers ignored all of it.
Second, just nine months earlier, the
Soviet Union held a referendum.
76.4% of citizens,
about 113 million people,
voted to preserve the USSR.
Under Soviet law, that vote was binding.
The three leaders
overruled it in a single night.
Third, the USSR had 15 republics.
Only three were in the room.
The other 12 weren't consulted.
When Mikhail Gorbachev learned what had
happened, he confronted Boris Yeltsin.
The three of you got together, but who
gave you any such authorization?
Even Leonid Kravchuk, one of
the signers, later admitted.
The signing of the Belavezha Accords
was a coup d'etat, which
was completed peacefully.
But the defense has answers.
First, the signers argued
they weren't seceding.
They were rescinding the 1922 treaty
that created the Soviet
Union in the first place.
Russia, Ukraine and Belarus were the
three of the four original founders.
The fourth, the Transcaucasian Republic,
had been dissolved in 1936.
Legal advisor Sergei Shakhrai argued that
since these republics tied
the political knot in 1922,
only they could untie it.
Second, by December 1991, the Soviet
state was already collapsing.
Historian Vladislav
Zubok called it a "carcass".
The August coup had failed.
Inflation reached 250% per month.
And just one week earlier, 90% of
Ukrainians voted for independence.
Third, two weeks after the accords were
signed, 11 republics
signed the Alma-Ata Declaration.
They retroactively
legitimized what had already been done.
So what's the verdict?
Under Soviet laws that existed in 1991,
the Belavezha Accords were almost
certainly unconstitutional.
Three republics made a
unilateral decision for 15.
They bypassed the secession law.
They ignored the binding referendum.
But historically, they formalized the
death of a state that
was already brain-dead.
And this is why it matters today.
In August 1991, four months before the
accords, Yeltsin's press
secretary Pavel Voshchanov,
issued a warning.
"Russia," he said, "reserved a right to
revise its boundaries with any republic
that left the Union."
He specifically named two
regions, Crimea and the Donbas.
14 years later, Vladimir Putin called the
Soviet collapse "the greatest
geopolitical catastrophe of the century".
And in 2022, Russia invaded Ukraine.
The Belavezha question isn't academic.
It's the legal argument Russia uses to
claim Ukraine's borders.
And Ukraine itself were never legitimate.
So what do you think?
Necessary dissolution?
Or historic theft?
Subscribe if you want more videos
examining the documents
behind modern conflicts.