Open Anderson's Popular History of the
United States from 1880. Look up what it
says about Columbus.
Columbus believed the earth to be round.
Now open the same
author's textbook from 1898.
Just 18 years later, the earth was flat
as a plate. One of the most
successful lies in western
history was manufactured in just 18 years
by textbook authors
rewriting their own books.
I went through the medieval manuscripts.
"Bede's
Reckoning of Time" from 725.
"Johannes de Sacrobosco's Sphere", the
standard university
astronomy textbook from 1230,
used for 400 years, surviving in hundreds
of manuscripts. They
all explicitly describe a
spherical earth. The flat earth myth was
invented by three specific
men to win cultural wars after
Darwin. Washington Irving in 1828, a
novelist who fabricated a
dramatic scene for his Columbus
biography. John Williams Draper in 1874,
angry at the Catholic
Church, turned fiction into
anti-religious propaganda. And Andrew
Dickinson White in 1896, he buried the
lie under a mountain
of footnotes and got it into every
textbook. Between 1870 and
1920, this fabrication entered
the curriculum and it's still being
thought today, despite historians
debunking it for 30 years.
Here's how they did it and why it
persists. And here's what's
at stake when we get medieval
history this wrong. The knowledge that
the earth is a sphere didn't
start in the middle ages. It
started with the ancient Greeks and they
didn't just theorize it,
they measured it. In 240 BC,
Eratosthenes of Cyrene used sticks and
shadows to calculate the earth's
circumference. We know this
from later Greek writers like Cleomedes
and Strabo who preserved his
method. At noon on the summer
solstice in Syene, modern Aswan, a
vertical stick cast no shadow. The sun
was directly overhead.
But in Alexandria, at the same exact
time, a stick cast a shadow at 7.2
degrees. If the sun's rays
are parallel, the only reason for
different shadow angles is the curvature
of the earth's surface.
7.2 degrees is 1 50th of a circle. So the
distance between the two
cities, about 5,000 stadia,
is 1 50th of the earth's circumference.
Total circumference, 250
000 stadia. Roughly 29,000
miles. The actual circumference 24,901
miles. In 240 BC, using sticks and
shadows, he got within
15%. This wasn't secret knowledge, this
was standard geography
thought throughout the classical
world and inherited by medieval scholars.
Jump to the year 630, the
dark ages have supposedly begun.
Isidore of Seville writes the
etymologies, the
encyclopedia of the medieval ages.
Isidore defines day and
night in book 3 chapter 51.
When the sun rises it creates the day,
and when it sets it
brings on the night, for
day is the sun over the earth, and night
is the sun under the
earth. The sun under the earth.
If the earth were a flat disk, how would
you explain night? The
sun goes behind a mountain,
gets extinguished, it doesn't go under
the ground you're
standing on. For the sun to pass
under the earth, the earth has to be
three-dimensional, it
requires a globe. Isidore
that it didn't need defending. Now jump
to 1230. Johannes de Sacrobosco writes
"Tractatus de Sphaera",
"Treatise on the Sphere". Here's the
critical thing, this was the
standard astronomy textbook
for 400 years. Required reading at every
university in Europe. How
manuscripts. What did it
teach? Chapter 1 provides sensory
proofs for the globe. The most famous,
the ship and mast
observation. Sacrobosco writes
"When a ship approaches land, a signal on
shore is visible from
the masthead, after it has
disappeared from the sight of someone at
the foot of the mast". And
there's no other explanation
of this thing than the bulge of the
water. Medieval students
weren't debating whether the
earth was round. They were learning
spherical geometry. How
latitude changes which stars you
see. How does the celestial equator
intersect the horizon differently in
Cairo versus London?
You cannot explain these observations
without a precise
three-dimensional model of a spherical
earth. But maybe you're thinking "okay,
scholars knew, what about regular
people?" It was public
knowledge. Literally in the king's hand.
This is the globus cruseger, the royal
orb, a golden sphere
surmounted by a cross. Medieval kings
held this in coronation
ceremonies from the 11th century
onwards. What did it represent?
Isidore of Seville explained:
Augustus is said to have
established the orb as a standard so that
he might the more display
the figure of the globe.
The sphere represents the earth. The
cross represented
Christ's sovereignty over it.
Were there any medieval writers who
thought the earth was flat? Yes, of
course. Two marginal
figures. Lactantius in the 4th century
and Cosmas Indicopleustes
in the 6th. As historian
Jeffrey Burton Russell put it, "Cosmos
had no followers
whatsoever. They were outliers,
ignored by the mainstream. The consensus
was clear." Most people
have heard some version of
the same story. Columbus standing in
front of churchmen who
insist the earth is flat,
of the world. That scene is usually
presented as medieval
ignorance versus modern thinking. What
almost nobody has told is
that this scene is supposed
to have a specific setting. A meeting in
1486 known as the Council
of Salamanca. And once you
know that, an obvious question follows.
If medieval scholars
already knew the earth was round,
what was Columbus actually arguing about
at Salamanca? Not
shape, size. Columbus made a
catastrophic double error, and we know
this from his own writings and
navigational logs that survive.
Error number one, he thought the earth
was smaller. Columbus's
estimate was about 20,000
miles circumference. How did he come to
this calculation? He used
measurements from a medieval
Persian geographer named Alfraganus who
said one degree equals 56
and two-thirds of a mile.
But Columbus thought Alfraganus meant the
Roman mile. Alfraganus
actually meant the Arabic mile,
which was nearly 50% longer. This
compounded his error. Columbus estimated
the voyage at about 20%
of its actual length. Error number two,
he thought Asia was bigger. He wildly
overestimated how far
Asia extended east. Consequently,
Columbus thought the distance from Spain
to Japan was maybe 2,500
miles. The scholars at Salamanca
correctly calculated it
was closer to 12,500 miles.
The Royal Commission at Salamanca wasn't
a panel of ignorant
monks citing the Bible.
It was headed by Hernando de Talavera,
Queen Isabella's
confessor. The commission included
professors of astronomy, geography,
mathematics, including the Jewish
astronomer Rabbi Abraham
Zaccuto. How do we know what they argued?
We know from the two main sources,
Bartolomé de las Casas,
the Spanish historian and Dominican friar
who had access to Columbus's papers and
interviewed people who were there, and
Ferdinand Columbus,
Christopher's own son who wrote a
biography of his father. According to
these accounts, the
commission told Columbus his
numbers were wrong. Not that the earth
was flat, that it was too big. They
correctly argued that if
the ocean was 12,500 miles wide,
Columbus's ships couldn't
carry enough food and water.
His crew would starve. And they were
right. Columbus was
saved by dumb luck. If the
Americans hadn't been setting exactly
where he thought Asia was,
his voyage would have been a
complete disaster. But history doesn't
like stories about
optimistic failures who get lucky.
History likes heroes battling ignorance.
Washington Irving gave history that hero.
In 1828, he invented an entire scene,
Columbus at the Council of Salamanca,
arguing with foolish
churchmen who insisted the earth must be
flat, pounding tables,
citing scripture, a scene that
never happened. Historian Samuel Elliott
Morrison later debunked
it. This is pure moonshine.
Washington Irving, sending his
opportunity for a picturesque and moving
scene, took a fictitious
account and let his imagination go
completely. But it was a bestseller. The
dramatic scene burned
into the public imagination as historical
fact. Irving gave the
world a simple story.
Enlightened Columbus versus flat-earth
religious zealots. It was
fiction, but it was useful fiction
and that brings us to the perpetrators.
Washington Irving was a novelist, not a
historian. In 1828, he published A
Voyages of Christopher Columbus. He was
writing a romantic epic for a young
American nation looking
for heroic founding figures. But every
hero needs a villain. And a dry
logistical debate about the
earth's circumference? Not so very
dramatic. So he fabricated the Salamanca
confrontation. Columbus
forced to argue against ignorant clerics
insisting the earth was flat. It sold
10,000 copies immediately.
Irving created the story. But why did it
have such a staying power?
Because it was waiting for someone
to weaponize it. 46 years later, John
William Draper takes Irving's account and
turns it into a weapon.
In 1874, Draper publishes History of the
Conflict Between Religion
and Science. That title says it
all. This book was designed to prove that
science and religion are
fundamentally incompatible,
locked in perpetual war. And to prove
this massive thesis, Draper needed
historical evidence,
smoking guns showing religion actively
suppressing scientific truth. Irving's
sitting there, waiting. Draper was
writing with a very specific target, the
Roman Catholic Church.
His book came out just four years after
the Vatican declared
papal infallibility in 1870,
a decision that caused massive backlash
amongst liberal
intellectuals. Draper seized the moment.
He used the flat earth myth as exhibit A.
The church had
systematically opposed scientific
progress throughout history. The Council
of Salamanca was his
star witness. The book again
was a bestseller. It went through over 50
printings and it armed a whole generation
of secular thinkers with what they
thought was undeniable
historical ammunition.
Irving created the story. Draper provided
the ideological engine.
And then, 22 years later,
Andrew Dickinson White provides the final
piece, Institutional
Backing. White's massive two-volume
work, The History of the Warfare of
Science with Theology in
Christendom, came out in 1896.
Modern historians call it more propaganda
than history. White was
the co-founder and first
president of Cornell University, a major
force in the movement for secular
education in America.
His technique, sheer volume, he buried
the flat earth story in
an avalanche of footnotes
and historical anecdotes. Many
cherry-picked, misleading,
or just wrong. He created an
impression of overwhelming scholarly
evidence. By citing Irving and Draper,
White gave the fiction
an air of academic respectability. And
thereby, the life flows
from popular book to scholarly
framework to textbook to common
knowledge. Why did this
specific myth become orthodoxy?
Why did it beat out 70 years of solid
historical evidence to the contrary?
Because it fulfilled a
powerful cultural need. In the late
1800s, intellectual elites
were fighting a cultural war.
Darwin's origin of species came out in
1859. The Catholic Church
declared papal infallibility
in 1870. Draper and White were neutral
historians. They were aggressive
participants. They used the
flat earth myth to prove a dethronement
narrative. That brave science
overcomes backward religion.
The flat earth story was the perfect
weapon. It was simple, dramatic,
emotionally satisfying.
It served the secular story of
redemption, contrasting
the dark ages with the sunlit
uplands of modern reason. And once it
entered textbooks, it became nearly
impossible to remove.
Which brings us to the question, if
historians debunked this 30 years ago,
why is this still being thought? Here's
the chronological
disparity that illustrates how
misinformation works. Historian Jeffrey
Burton Russell surveyed
19th century American history
textbooks. Before 1870, very few
mentioned the flat earth myth. After
1880, almost all of them
featured the legend. What changed? The
lie entered the culture
between 1828 and 1896.
Irving, Draper, White. By the time
historians started
debunking it seriously in the 1990s,
the lie had a 150 year head start.
Jeffrey Burton Russell's Inventing the
Flat Earth came out in
1991. That should have ended it. It
didn't. The truth never reached the
textbooks or culture at
large. Why? Because the lie is more
exciting than the truth. The truth is
that the medieval period
was intellectually complex. The Roman
Catholic Church never even
took an official stance on
the earth shape. That's boring. The lie
is that brave Columbus fought
ignorant priests who thought
he'd sail off the edge of the world.
That's dramatic. It fits a
bigger story we want to believe.
The lone genius against the ignorant mob.
The story feels more true
than the truth. And that's
the systemic weakness. This is a case
study in the lag between academic
knowledge and public knowledge.
Powerful, emotionally satisfying stories
are sticky. They're
impervious to evidence,
which is a huge lesson for right now.
Between 2020 and 2023,
trust in science dropped 15%.
Today, 27% of Americans have little to no
confidence in
scientists. And one of the tools
in reminding that trust is this exact
myth. Modern flat earthers claim the
church used to teach that
the earth was flat as proof that experts
suppress the truth. They
use this to justify rejecting
climate science, vaccine research, and
evolution. Research shows a gateway
effect. Believe in one
historical myth makes it easier to
believe contemporary
conspiracies. Once you believe
historians fabricated the flat earthed
story, it's easier to
believe scientists are fabricating
climate data, or vaccine efficacy, or
evolution evidence. Here's
the profound irony that reveals
how misinformation gets repurposed. In
the 19th century, this myth
was created by academic elites
for high-minded and anti-clerical reasons.
They used it to promote
rationality, to professionalize
science, to give science more authority
over religious
institutions. It was a tool to build
up the expert elite. Today, modern
populist movements have
inherited that exact myth,
but they flipped it. Now some use it to
oppose the expert elite,
to attack orthodox science,
to justify distrust of NASA,
universities, the scientific
establishment. They appeal to
common sense against what they call
mystifying theories. Their
argument, if they lied to you
about Columbus and the medieval church
back then, why wouldn't they
be lying to you now about NASA,
about the photos from space, about
climate change? Same lie,
first used to build up the
authority of science, now used to tear it
down. This isn't just about medieval
history. The failure
to debunk this old lie isn't really about
the facts. The facts are clear. It's
about the narrative's
emotional power, its utility. It's
utility in propping up an
identity. The identity of the
brave skeptic who trusts their own eyes
over the experts. And you
see the exact same mechanism in
anti-vaccine movements and climate
denial. It's the same playbook. Old
misinformation becomes
the foundation for new distrust. That's
why this matters. We
opened with two textbooks,
Anderson 1880 versus Anderson in 1898. In
18 years, the same author
rewrote his own textbook.
And one of the most successful lies in
Western history was
embedded in the curriculum.
The evidence proves medieval scholars
knew the earth was a sphere.
royal orb. Columbus wasn't
arguing about shape, but size.
And he was wrong. The flat earth myth
was deliberately
fabricated by three men across 70
years for political reasons. It entered
textbooks to serve
19th century culture wars.
It persists because it's useful. First
for rationalists, now
for conspiracy theorists.
The only defense is what we've done here.
Go back to the primary sources,
check the medieval documents, see what
they actually wrote. Because if
historians and propagandists
successfully fabricated this universally
accepted myth for over a century, what
other facts we think
we know might also be carefully
constructed historical
fictions. Check the sources,
question the narratives, demand evidence,
not just for medieval
history, for everything.