At Ole Miss, Vance made a lot of claims.
In this video we will
look at three of them.
Christianity invented human rights, the
founders wanted
Christianity in government,
and Christian civilization is the most
moral in history. I went
to the Vatican archives,
I pulled up papal documents from the
1800s, I checked what
Madison and Adams actually wrote.
I found papal bulls from 1452, looked at
what Protestant
reformers said about slavery.
Here's what I found.
Human rights, the very idea that human
beings have rights,
are a Christian concept.
Vance says Christianity invented human
rights and human dignity.
This is a common claim in
conservative Christian circles, but I
checked church documents.
In 1832, 56 years after the
Declaration of Independence, Pope Gregory
XVI publishes "Mirari Vos"
section 14, exact quote.
This shameful font of indifferentism
gives rise to the absurd
and erroneous proposition
which claims that liberty of conscience
must be maintained for everyone.
The Pope is calling freedom of conscience
absurd, but it gets worse.
Watch what the Pope said 32
years later. 1864, Pope Pius IX publishes
the Syllabus of
Errors, a numbered list of
80 modern ideas that are condemned. Error
15, religious freedom.
Error 77, ending Catholic
only states. Error 78, allowing other
religions to worship
publicly. This is 1864, the Catholic
church is officially condemning religious
freedom as an error. Maybe
that's just the Catholics.
What about Protestants? Martin Luther in
the 1520s says governments
are ordained by God to maintain
order. Individual conscience matters for
salvation, but not for
challenging authority.
John Calvin establishes Geneva as a
theocracy. In 1553, he burns Michael
Servetus at the stake
for heresy. For 300 years after the
Reformation, Protestant states enforced
religious conformity
just like Catholic ones. And here's the
part nobody mentions.
When does Christian human
rights language actually show up?
Historian at Yale Samuel
Moyn documented it. The phrase
gets invented in the 1940s after World
War II. A theologian named
Charles Malik working at the UN
starts claiming Christianity always
supported human rights.
Moyn shows that's retrofitting.
For most of Christian history, the
political model was hierarchy. Divine
right of kings, church backing
monarchy. This is where the story flips.
1965, the second Vatican Council.
Declaration on religious
freedom. The Catholic church reverses its
position. It says people have
a right to religious liberty,
but that is 101 years after condemning
it. And almost 2000 years
after Christianity began.
Did Christianity invent human rights?
Major churches were condemning these
concepts in the 1800s.
They changed positions in the 1900s after
Enlightenment philosophy pressured them.
That's not inventing rights. That's
eventually accepting them.
So if churches opposed rights,
what about the founders? When our
founders talked about freedom of
religion, they didn't
mean you weren't allowed to say a
Christian prayer in a public school or
that you weren't allowed to
talk about Jesus Christ in a public
forum. Massachusetts
required Protestant leaders.
Multiple states had official churches,
but the founders
completely disagreed on this.
Here's what Madison says about 1,500
years of established
Christianity. During almost 15
centuries has the legal establishment of
Christianity been on
trial? What have been
its fruits? More or less in all places,
pride and indolence in
the clergy, ignorance and
servility in the laity. In both,
superstition, bigotry and persecution.
Madison's whole argument
is that Christianity did better without
government support. John
Adams completely disagreed. He's
writing to Jefferson saying
Christianity's principles
are "eternal and immutable".
But then in 1797, Adams signs the Treaty
of Tripoli. Article
11, the government of the
United States is not in any sense founded
on the Christian
religion. The same guy who praised
Christianity signed a treaty saying
America isn't founded on it.
That's the point. The founders
didn't agree, not even with themselves.
This isn't consensus.
They're actively arguing.
What does religious freedom look like in
early America? 1844
Philadelphia. Catholic-Protestant
riots over which Bible version to use in
schools. Over 4,000 troops
deployed. At least 20 people
killed. 1834 Charlestown, Massachusetts.
Mob burns down an
Ursuline convent. Mormons are
expelled from Missouri in 1838. Joseph
Smith is murdered in
Illinois in 1844. In 1857,
President Buchanan sends 5,000 troops to
Utah. Historian David
Sehat calls this the moral
establishment. States using law to
enforce Protestant
Christianity even after official
disestablishment ended. Did the
founders want Christianity in public
life? Some did. Some didn't.
They disagreed so fundamentally that
while Adams was president, the Senate
unanimously ratified a
treaty saying America isn't founded on
Christianity. The Supreme Court didn't
invent separation of
church and state. It ended the Protestant
establishment that
excluded everyone else.
Now for the big claim. Is Christian
civilization the most moral in history?
1452 Pope Nicholas V issues a papal bull
called Dum Diversas
addressed to the king of Portugal.
Reading directly from the Latin
translation, the Pope grants Portugal
full and free permission
to invade, search out, capture and
subjugate the Saracens and
Pagans and any unbelievers and
to reduce their persons to perpetual
slavery. Perpetual slavery,
authorized by the Pope in 1452,
three years later in 1455, Romanus
Pontifex authorizes the
Portuguese slave trade.
1493 Inter Caetera divides the entire new
world between Spain and
Portugal. Maybe that's just
Catholics. What about the Protestants?
Martin Luther says rebellion against
masters is rebellion
against God. Southern Presbyterian
theologian James Henley
Thornwell in the 1850s says slavery
is the condition in which infinite wisdom
has been pleased to place
them. Catholic and Protestant
theologians defended slavery for over
a thousand years. What about Christians
who weren't enslaved?
How did Christian authorities treat
people they called heretics?
1487 Two Catholic inquisitors published
the Malleus
Maleficarum, The Hammer of Witches.
It's a manual how to identify witches,
how to torture them, how to execute them.
Church approved. Between 1400 and 1782
European Christian
authorities executed an estimated
40,000 to 60,000 people for witchcraft.
80% of them were women.
Protestant areas were just as
brutal. Scotland executed 4,000, Germany
executed 25,000, Martin
Luther supported witch hunts,
John Calvin presided over witch trials in
Geneva. Catholic
inquisitors, Protestant reformers,
same outcome. The Southern Baptist
Convention was founded in 1845 to defend
slavery. The Methodist
church split over it in 1844.
Presbyterian church split in
1861. And this matters today
because this same argument is now back in
school curriculums. Florida's 2023
curriculum standards
say enslaved people developed skills
which in some instances
could be applied for their
personal benefit. PragerU videos claim
Christianity ended slavery without
mentioning the 1,400 years
it spent defending it. The country who
abolished slavery first in
the Americas was Haiti in 1804.
They defeated three Christian empires
trying to keep them
enslaved. France, Britain and Spain.
Britain abolishes slavery in 1833 but
that's after Haiti. And
British abolition came after
decades of pressure from Enlightenment
thinkers and Quaker
activists. Brazil, a Catholic nation,
was the last to abolish slavery in the
Americas in 1888. Christians were
involved in abolition of
course. Wilberforce, Quakers, many
abolitionists were devout
Christians but they were fighting
other Christians using the same Bible.
For 1,400 years the pro-slavery
Christians were the majority.
The Christian abolitionists were the
minority challenging
centuries of church teaching.
So three claims checked. Did Christianity
invent human rights?
Major churches condemned those concepts
in the 1800s. They
changed positions in the 1900s.
That's not inventing rights, that's
eventually accepting them. Did the
founders want Christianity
in government? Madison and Adams
completely disagreed. There's no
consensus on this. The
treaty they ratified says America isn't
founded on Christianity. Is Christian
civilization the most
moral? 1,400 years of theological defense
of slavery? Papal bulls authorizing it?
Protestant reformers defending it? 40,000
people executed for
witchcraft using church approved
manuals? Major denominations splitting to
defend slavery in the 1840s.
When you claim Christianity
invented human rights and is the most
moral civilization, you're
teaching kids a version of
the past that erases the majority
Christian position for over a millennium.
That's not education,
that's selective history. In my previous
video I fact-checked
JD Vance on colonialism.
If you want more evidence-based debunking
using primary sources,
subscribe. Thanks for watching.