35 countries recognized Somaliland in
1960, then they all forgot.
This is where 12% of global trade passes
and where 5 powers are
now competing for control.
Ethiopia is landlocked and
desperate for port access.
China, UAE, Turkey, Israel all want in.
And right in the middle, a functioning
democracy with its own government,
currency and borders
that the world pretends doesn't exist.
In December 2025, Israel became the first
UN member to formally
recognize Somaliland.
Somalia called it an attack. The African
Union rejected it within hours.
I went to the documents. The 1963 treaty
it was never signed,
the 1963 court ruling,
the African Union's own investigation
they've been ignoring for 20 years.
And here's what I found and why both
narratives get this wrong.
Britain controlled the Somaliland
Protectorate from 1884, a separate colony
with its own borders.
By 1960,
decolonization was sweeping Africa.
On June 26, 1960, the Somaliland Order in
Council came into effect.
Reading directly from the act, the
territories known as the
Somaliland Protectorate
shall become an independent country on
the 26th day of June, 1960.
Not a promise, not a
transition, independence.
Within hours the telegrams arrived.
China's foreign minister sent
congratulations before
independence even took effect.
On June 25, the US followed on June 26.
The Soviet Union, Britain, France, Egypt,
Ethiopia, Ghana, Israel.
More than 35 states extended formal
recognition through bilateral agreements,
establishing de jure statehood.
Somaliland existed as an independent,
recognized state for five days.
Then came July 1st.
The plan was unification.
British Somaliland in the north, Italian
Somalia in the south.
Same ethnic group, two
colonies, one new republic.
On July 1st, 1960, Italian
Somalia gained independence.
The same day, both
territories declared themselves unified.
But here's where the
legal problem begins.
Somaliland passed the union
of Somaliland and Somalia law.
On June 27, Somalia passed the
Atto di Unione on June 30.
Two different
parliaments, two laws, one union.
Except they weren't the same law.
Eugene Cotran was a legal scholar who
examined the union documents
while they were still fresh.
Reading from his analysis, the union of
Somaliland and Somalia law
and the Somalia Act of Union were both
drafted in the form of
bilateral agreements.
But neither of them was signed by the
representatives of the two territories.
It gets worse.
The Somalia Act of Union was approved in
principle, but never enacted into law.
Somalia's parliament even passed a
resolution requesting
a definitive single text of the Act of
Union to be submitted to the National
Assembly for approval.
That text was never created.
This isn't academic.
It was tested in court.
In 1963, a British
judge named Hazelwood ruled,
in the absence of an Act of Union, the
court had no
jurisdiction over Somaliland.
Somalia did try to fix this.
On January 31, 1961, law number five
attempted to
retroactively validate the union.
Cotran's analysis
again, the Act of Union,
deemed to have come
into effect on July 1960,
deemed retroactive
legislation curing a void agreement.
Whether you can retroactively fix a
defect this
fundamental, scholars disagree.
But the defect itself isn't disputed.
So how does Somalia defend the union
built on paperwork that doesn't exist?
Let me present Somalia's side fairly.
The strongest version
of this argument matters.
First, the union was voluntary.
Northerners can in no way claim that the
1960 merger was a shotgun wedding.
By all accounts,
unification was wildly popular.
That is true.
There were celebrations.
Pan-Somali nationalism
was a dominant force.
This wasn't conquest.
Second, the international community
recognized the union.
A full union had in fact been affected by
the will of the peoples,
and such union was recognized by the
international community.
The UN admitted the Somali
Republic on September 20, 1960.
Every nation accepted the unified state.
Third, 31 years of practice.
The state continued to exist as a single
national entity for
more than two decades,
regardless of any legal shortcomings.
These are legitimate arguments, and
they're why this case is
harder than either side admits.
The question is whether practice and
recognition can cure a
treaty defect this fundamental.
The Somali Republic
didn't just fail, it imploded.
By 1991, the Siad
Barre regime had collapsed.
The South descended into warlord chaos.
The North, former British Somaliland,
took a different path.
On May 18, 1991,
elders gathered in Burao.
Their declaration was carefully worded.
The country previously known as
Somaliland has restored its independence.
Not declared, restored.
That framing matters.
James Crawford, the most
cited scholar on statehood,
defines secession as the creation of a
state by the use of force
without the consent of
the former sovereign.
Somaliland's argument,
they're not succeeding,
they're restoring sovereignty that
existed on June 26, 1960,
from a union that was
never legally completed.
And there's precedent.
In the 1990s, the Baltic states didn't
declare independence.
They restored it.
Recovery of
sovereignty suppressed in 1940.
The international
community accepted that framing
because they'd never recognized the
suppression as legal.
But there's a key difference.
The world never recognized the 1940
Soviet annexation as legal.
The 1960 Somaliland Union
was recognized for 31 years.
Whether that difference is
fatal depends on who's deciding.
And for 20 years, the African Union has
been the one deciding.
Remember that investigation I mentioned?
In April 2005, the AU sent a fact-finding
mission to Somaliland.
Their conclusion, the fact that the union
between Somaliland and
Somalia was never ratified,
makes Somaliland's search for
recognition historically unique
and self-justified in
African political history.
That is not my interpretation.
That's the AU's own fact-finding mission.
But there's more.
Objectively viewed, the case should not
be linked to the notion
of opening a Pandora's box.
The AU distinguished Somaliland from
other secessionist movements.
Unlike Biafra or Katanga, regions
breaking from their
original colonial unit,
Somaliland is a complete colonial unit,
leaving a failed merger.
Their recommendation?
The AU should find a special method of
dealing with this outstanding case.
That was 20 years ago.
No special method was ever found and no
action was ever taken.
Here's the irony.
In the constitutive act of the African
Union of 2000, we see
in the principle section,
respect of borders existing on
achievement of independence.
But Somaliland's borders
are the colonial borders.
By refusing to recognize those borders,
the AU is arguably
violating its own doctrine.
Ethiopia broke the
logjam in January 2024.
Prime Minister Abiy Ahmed called Red Sea
access an existential question.
Reliance on Djibouti's
port was expensive and risky.
The deal was this.
Ethiopia leased support
at Berbera for 50 years.
In exchange, Ethiopia agreed to an
in-depth assessment towards recognition.
Not a guarantee, but the clearest signal
yet from a major African power.
Then, Israel went further.
Prime Minister Netanyahu announced a full
diplomatic recognition,
including the exchange of ambassadors and
the opening of embassies.
Israel, the first UN member to formally
recognize Somaliland in 34 years.
Somalia called it an
attack on sovereignty.
Within hours, the African Union responded
by firmly rejecting
any initiative aimed at
recognizing Somaliland.
The same union that called the case
"unique" and "self-justified"
now calls recognition
a dangerous precedent.
So what's happening here?
Somaliland isn't trying
to become independent.
They're arguing they already were.
For five days in 1960,
recognized by 35 nations,
before a union that was
never properly ratified,
the documents support this.
The 1963 ruling supports this.
The African Union's own investigation
called it "unique" and "self-justified".
That first narrative, Somaliland is just
a separatist region with no legal basis.
The 1960 independence, the 35
recognitions, the Never-Ratified Treaty,
the 2005 report, that under a concept.
But the second narrative, Somaliland was
never part of Somalia.
The 31 years of practice, the
international recognition,
and the voluntary
merger, that complicates it.
The legal case is stronger
than most people realize.
The political obstacles are real.
The African Union fears that recognition
would spur more secessionist cases.
South Sudan is the only
modern African secession.
And that required parent-state consent.
Somalia will never consent.
Which means the
international community has to decide.
Does documentary evidence
trump political convenience?
Somaliland is not merely de facto.
It is de jure by virtue of its
independence on June 26, 1960.
The failure to
acknowledge this is not ambiguity.
It is a political choice.
Israel just made that
choice impossible to ignore.
The documents exist.
The precedents exist.
The AU's own investigation called it
"unique" and "self-justified".
The only thing missing is the
political will to read them.
If you want to understand how colonial
decisions still shape modern
conflicts, please subscribe.